<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Hansard xml:lang="EN" id="10720789">
  <StartPageNumber>29463</StartPageNumber>
  <DocumentTitle>
    <DocumentName>OFFICIAL REPORT (HANSARD)</DocumentName>
  </DocumentTitle>
  <ExtractedInformation>
    <ExtractedItem Name="InstitutionDebate">House of Commons Debates</ExtractedItem>
    <ExtractedItem Name="Volume">VOLUME 148</ExtractedItem>
    <ExtractedItem Name="Number">NUMBER 438</ExtractedItem>
    <ExtractedItem Name="Session">1st SESSION</ExtractedItem>
    <ExtractedItem Name="Parliament">42nd PARLIAMENT</ExtractedItem>
    <ExtractedItem Name="Date">Thursday, June 20, 2019</ExtractedItem>
    <ExtractedItem Name="SpeakerName">Speaker: The Honourable Geoff Regan</ExtractedItem>
    <ExtractedItem Name="Institution">HOUSE OF COMMONS</ExtractedItem>
    <ExtractedItem Name="Country">CANADA</ExtractedItem>
    <ExtractedItem Name="TOCNote">(Table of Contents appears at back of this issue.)</ExtractedItem>
    <ExtractedItem Name="HeaderTitle">COMMONS DEBATES</ExtractedItem>
    <ExtractedItem Name="HeaderDate">June 20, 2019</ExtractedItem>
    <ExtractedItem Name="MetaDocumentCategory">DEBATES</ExtractedItem>
    <ExtractedItem Name="MetaTitle">Edited Hansard * Table of Contents * Number 438 (Official Version)</ExtractedItem>
    <ExtractedItem Name="MetaTitleEn">Official Report * Table of Contents * Number 438 (Official Version)</ExtractedItem>
    <ExtractedItem Name="MetaTitleFr">Compte rendu officiel * Table des matières * Numéro 438 (Version officielle)</ExtractedItem>
    <ExtractedItem Name="MetaVolumeNumber">VOLUME 148</ExtractedItem>
    <ExtractedItem Name="MetaNumberNumber">438</ExtractedItem>
    <ExtractedItem Name="MetaDateNumDay">20</ExtractedItem>
    <ExtractedItem Name="MetaDateNumMonth">06</ExtractedItem>
    <ExtractedItem Name="MetaDateNumYear">2019</ExtractedItem>
    <ExtractedItem Name="MetaCreationTime">2019/06/20 10:05:00</ExtractedItem>
    <ExtractedItem Name="InstitutionDebateFr">Débats de la Chambre des communes</ExtractedItem>
    <ExtractedItem Name="InstitutionDebateEn">House of Commons Debates</ExtractedItem>
    <ExtractedItem Name="MetaInstitution">House Of Commons</ExtractedItem>
    <ExtractedItem Name="SessionNumber">1</ExtractedItem>
    <ExtractedItem Name="ParliamentNumber">42</ExtractedItem>
    <ExtractedItem Name="InCameraNote">
    </ExtractedItem>
  </ExtractedInformation>
  <HansardBody>
    <Intro>
      <ParaText id="6005084">The House met at 10 a.m.</ParaText>
      <Prayer>Prayer</Prayer>
      <SubjectOfBusiness id="10720798">
        <Timestamp Hr="10" Mn="05">(1005)</Timestamp>
        <FloorLanguage language="EN">[<I>English</I>]</FloorLanguage>
        <SubjectOfBusinessTitle>Business of the House</SubjectOfBusinessTitle>
        <SubjectOfBusinessQualifier>Mark Warawa</SubjectOfBusinessQualifier>
        <SubjectOfBusinessContent>
          <Intervention Type="Debate" ToC="Yes" ToCText="Ms. Bergen" id="10720799">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="224944" Type="7">Hon. Candice Bergen (House Leader of the Official Opposition, CPC)</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="6005085">Mr. Speaker, I rise on a point of order.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6005086">We have just received the sad news that our colleague Mark Warawa, the member for <Affiliation DbId="213926" Type="2">Langley—Aldergrove</Affiliation>, has passed away.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6005087"> I believe that if you seek it, you will receive unanimous consent to go through Routine Proceedings and then to suspend the House until 12 noon.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Debate" ToC="No" ToCText="The Speaker" id="10720800">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="214706" Type="15">The Speaker</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="6005088">Is there unanimous consent?</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6005089">
                <B>Some hon. members:</B> Agreed.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6005090">
                <B>The Speaker:</B> We will be speaking more later, about our dear friend Mark.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
        </SubjectOfBusinessContent>
      </SubjectOfBusiness>
    </Intro>
    <OrderOfBusiness id="10720803" Rubric="RoutineProceedings">
      <OrderOfBusinessTitle>ROUTINE PROCEEDINGS</OrderOfBusinessTitle>
      <CatchLine>Routine Proceedings</CatchLine>
      <SubjectOfBusiness id="10720804">
        <FloorLanguage language="EN">[<I>English</I>]</FloorLanguage>
        <SubjectOfBusinessTitle>Parliamentary Budget Officer</SubjectOfBusinessTitle>
        <SubjectOfBusinessContent>
          <Intervention Type="Debate" ToC="Yes" ToCText="The Speaker" id="10720853">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="214706" Type="15">The Speaker</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="6005091">Pursuant to subsection 79.2(2) of the Parliament of Canada Act, it is my duty to present to the House a report from the Parliamentary Budget Officer, entitled “Election Proposal Costing Baseline”.</ParaText>
              <FloorLanguage language="FR">[<I>Translation</I>]</FloorLanguage>
              <ParaText id="6005092"> Pursuant to section 79.22 of the Parliament of Canada Act, it is my duty to present to the House a report from the Parliamentary Budget Officer entitled “2018-19 Report on the Activities of the Office of the Parliamentary Budget Officer”.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
        </SubjectOfBusinessContent>
      </SubjectOfBusiness>
      <SubjectOfBusiness id="10720871">
        <FloorLanguage language="EN">[<I>English</I>]</FloorLanguage>
        <SubjectOfBusinessTitle>Chief Electoral Officer</SubjectOfBusinessTitle>
        <SubjectOfBusinessContent>
          <Intervention Type="Debate" ToC="Yes" ToCText="The Speaker" id="10720868">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="214706" Type="15">The Speaker</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="6005093">I have the honour to lay upon the table the report of the Chief Electoral Officer on alternative signatures. This report is deemed permanently referred to the Standing Committee on Procedure and House Affairs.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
        </SubjectOfBusinessContent>
      </SubjectOfBusiness>
      <SubjectOfBusiness id="10720877">
        <SubjectOfBusinessTitle>Standing Senate Committee on Aboriginal Peoples</SubjectOfBusinessTitle>
        <SubjectOfBusinessContent>
          <Intervention Type="Debate" ToC="Yes" ToCText="Mr. Blair" id="10720805">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="241632" Type="4">Hon. Bill Blair (Minister of Border Security and Organized Crime Reduction, Lib.)</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="6005094">Mr. Speaker, pursuant to Standing Order 32(2) I have the honour to table, in both official languages, the progress report on priorities identified in the 11th report of the Standing Senate Committee on Aboriginal Peoples, entitled, “The subject matter of Bill C-45, An Act respecting cannabis and to amend the Controlled Drugs and Substances Act, the Criminal Code and other Acts”.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
        </SubjectOfBusinessContent>
      </SubjectOfBusiness>
      <SubjectOfBusiness id="10720899">
        <FloorLanguage language="FR">[<I>Translation</I>]</FloorLanguage>
        <SubjectOfBusinessTitle>Office of the Ombudsman for the Department of National Defence and the Canadian Armed Forces </SubjectOfBusinessTitle>
        <SubjectOfBusinessContent>
          <Intervention Type="Debate" ToC="Yes" ToCText="Mr. Cormier" id="10720807">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="242062" Type="18">Mr. Serge Cormier (Parliamentary Secretary to the Minister of National Defence, Lib.)</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="6005095">Mr. Speaker, pursuant to Standing Order 32(2), I have the honour to table, in both official languages, a document entitled “2018-19 Annual Report for the Office of the Ombudsman for the Department of National Defence and the Canadian Armed Forces”.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
        </SubjectOfBusinessContent>
      </SubjectOfBusiness>
      <SubjectOfBusiness id="10720900">
        <SubjectOfBusinessTitle>Export of Military Goods from Canada</SubjectOfBusinessTitle>
        <SubjectOfBusinessContent>
          <Intervention Type="Debate" ToC="Yes" ToCText="Mr. Oliphant" id="10720809">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="248633" Type="18">Mr. Robert Oliphant (Parliamentary Secretary to the Minister of Foreign Affairs, Lib.)</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="6005096">Mr. Speaker, pursuant to Standing Order 32(2), I have the honour to table, in both official languages, the 2018 report on exports of military goods from Canada, and the 2018 annual report to Parliament on the administration of the Export and Import Permits Act.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
        </SubjectOfBusinessContent>
      </SubjectOfBusiness>
      <SubjectOfBusiness id="10720881">
        <FloorLanguage language="EN">[<I>English</I>]</FloorLanguage>
        <SubjectOfBusinessTitle>Government Response to Petitions</SubjectOfBusinessTitle>
        <SubjectOfBusinessContent>
          <Intervention Type="Debate" ToC="Yes" ToCText="Mr. Lamoureux" id="10720811">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="214668" Type="18">Mr. Kevin Lamoureux (Parliamentary Secretary to the Leader of the Government in the House of Commons, Lib.)</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="6005097">Mr. Speaker, pursuant to Standing Order 36(8), I have the honour to table, in both official languages, the government's response to 34 petitions.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
        </SubjectOfBusinessContent>
      </SubjectOfBusiness>
      <SubjectOfBusiness id="10720814">
        <FloorLanguage language="FR">[<I>Translation</I>]</FloorLanguage>
        <SubjectOfBusinessTitle>Interparliamentary Delegations</SubjectOfBusinessTitle>
        <SubjectOfBusinessContent>
          <Intervention Type="Debate" ToC="Yes" ToCText="Mr. Samson" id="10720813">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="214334" Type="2">Mr. Darrell Samson (Sackville—Preston—Chezzetcook, Lib.)</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="6005098">Mr. Speaker, pursuant to Standing Order 34(1), I have the honour to present to the House, in both official languages, the report of the delegation of the Canadian branch of the Assemblée parlementaire de la Francophonie, concerning its participation in the Bureau Meeting and the 44th Ordinary Session of the APF, held in Quebec City, from July 5 to 10, 2018.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
        </SubjectOfBusinessContent>
      </SubjectOfBusiness>
      <SubjectOfBusiness id="10720820">
        <FloorLanguage language="EN">[<I>English</I>]</FloorLanguage>
        <SubjectOfBusinessTitle>Committees of the House</SubjectOfBusinessTitle>
        <SubjectOfBusinessQualifier>Public Safety and National Security</SubjectOfBusinessQualifier>
        <SubjectOfBusinessContent>
          <Intervention Type="Debate" ToC="Yes" ToCText="Mr. McKay" id="10720816">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="213903" Type="2">Hon. John McKay (Scarborough—Guildwood, Lib.)</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="6005099">Mr. Speaker, I have the honour to present, in both official languages, the unanimous 38th report of the Standing Committee on Public Safety and National Security, entitled “Cybersecurity in the Financial Sector as a National Security Issue”. </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6005100">The reason this report is unanimous is that the members worked together in a fashion that would do credit to our Parliament and the functioning of committees. I particularly want to take this opportunity to single out each of the members of the committee for their contributions, particularly the member for <Affiliation DbId="214029" Type="2">Montarville</Affiliation> for his experience as a CBSA officer and his quarterbacking skills; the member for <Affiliation DbId="214137" Type="2">Laurentides—Labelle</Affiliation>, who speaks faster than I can think; the member for <Affiliation DbId="214078" Type="2">Mississauga—Lakeshore</Affiliation> for his thoughtful interventions; the member for <Affiliation DbId="214009" Type="2">Brampton North</Affiliation> for her practical insights; and the member for <Affiliation DbId="214035" Type="2">Toronto—Danforth</Affiliation> for her really pointed questions. </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6005101">I also want to recognize the vice-chair, the member for <Affiliation DbId="214522" Type="2">Charlesbourg—Haute-Saint-Charles</Affiliation>, for his really helpful steering of the committee; the member for <Affiliation DbId="227983" Type="2">Medicine Hat—Cardston—Warner</Affiliation>, who asked very pointed questions from his police background; as well as the member for <Affiliation DbId="214458" Type="2">Yellowhead</Affiliation>, who also asked very pointed questions due to his police background; and the member for <Affiliation DbId="214060" Type="2">Beloeil—Chambly</Affiliation>, who was reasonable and helpful throughout the entire committee process. It is a real example of how, when committees work together, they will succeed and provide very helpful insight.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6005102">Finally, I want to draw members' attention to the first recommendation of the committee, which states, “The Committee recommends that, in the next Parliament, the House of Commons Standing Committee on Public Safety and National Security establish a sub-committee dedicated to studying the public safety and national security aspects of cybersecurity, with potential areas of inquiry including international approaches to critical infrastructure protection, impact of emerging technologies, and cyber supply chain security.” One of the things we really learned out of this study was that this field is moving so fast that the Parliament of Canada needs to stay on top of cybersecurity in all of its manifestations. </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6005103">It has been a great honour for me to have chaired that committee and I would like to think the success of the committee is entirely due to the co-operation among the members. I look forward to the government's response tabled pursuant to Standing Order 109.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
        </SubjectOfBusinessContent>
      </SubjectOfBusiness>
      <SubjectOfBusiness id="10720828">
        <Timestamp Hr="10" Mn="10">(1010)</Timestamp>
        <SubjectOfBusinessTitle>Royal Canadian Mounted Police Day Act</SubjectOfBusinessTitle>
        <SubjectOfBusinessContent>
          <Intervention Type="Debate" ToC="Yes" ToCText="Mr. Arnold" id="10720822">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="214444" Type="2">Mr. Mel Arnold (North Okanagan—Shuswap, CPC) </Affiliation>
            </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ProceduralText TocType="TPC" id="1">Bill C-467. Introduction and first reading</ProceduralText>
              <ParaText id="6005104"> moved for leave to introduce Bill <Document DbId="10586469" Type="4">C-467, An Act to establish Royal Canadian Mounted Police Day</Document>.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6005105"> He said: Mr. Speaker, I am honoured to have the opportunity to present this private member's bill today, seconded by my good friend and colleague, the member for <Affiliation DbId="214458" Type="2">Yellowhead</Affiliation>. This initiative was started by a small group of constituents in my riding of North Okanagan—Shuswap and the support has grown exponentially across the region, the province and now the country.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6005106">February 1, 2020, will mark the 100th anniversary of the forming of the Royal Canadian Mounted Police. For almost a century, they have been defending the law, “<I>Maintiens le droit</I>”. This bill would designate February 1 each year as Royal Canadian Mounted Police day. I recognize that it is the end of this 42nd Parliament, but I look forward to returning in the 43rd Parliament to ensure our national police force, the Royal Canadian Mounted Police, are recognized for their 100th anniversary.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6005107">I want to thank members in my riding, Martin von Holst and Guy Bailey, for their incredible work on this and I look forward to moving this forward when we return in the fall.</ParaText>
              <ProceduralText TocType="TCC" id="2">(Motions deemed adopted, bill read the first time and printed)</ProceduralText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
        </SubjectOfBusinessContent>
      </SubjectOfBusiness>
      <SubjectOfBusiness id="10720880">
        <SubjectOfBusinessTitle>Employment Equity Act</SubjectOfBusinessTitle>
        <SubjectOfBusinessContent>
          <Intervention Type="Debate" ToC="Yes" ToCText="Mrs. Caesar-Chavannes" id="10720833">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="214048" Type="2">Mrs. Celina Caesar-Chavannes (Whitby, Ind.) </Affiliation>
            </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ProceduralText TocType="TPC" id="3">Bill C-468. Introduction and first reading</ProceduralText>
              <ParaText id="6005108">, seconded by the member for <Affiliation DbId="214558" Type="2">Vancouver Granville</Affiliation>, moved for leave to introduce Bill <Document DbId="10588592" Type="4">C-468, An Act to amend the Employment Equity Act</Document>.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6005109"> She said: Mr. Speaker, it gives me great honour to present this bill in what will be my last act as a member of Parliament.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6005110">I would first like to offer my condolences to the family and friends of <Affiliation DbId="213926" Type="2">Mr. Mark Warawa</Affiliation>, and the community of <Affiliation DbId="213926" Type="2">Langley—Aldergrove</Affiliation>. His last speech in this place will be remembered as one of my favourites.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6005111">I want to thank the member for <Affiliation DbId="214558" Type="2">Vancouver Granville</Affiliation>, a woman I am very proud of and will always continue to stand with.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6005112">I want to thank the members of the Liberal government and the NDP for supporting this bill from the outset, and particularly the members for <Affiliation DbId="214460" Type="2">Portage—Lisgar</Affiliation> and <Affiliation DbId="214088" Type="2">Oshawa</Affiliation> who helped and guided me through this process to get this bill here today. I want to thank Jacqueline Yost, legislative counsel; and the Office of the Law Clerk and Parliamentary Counsel for all of their help in getting me here.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6005113">I came to this place to be a voice for all the people I represent, to raise awareness on issues, to move the status quo and to remove barriers.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6005114">This bill represents the voices of those both past and present in the federal system. It is my hope that it will examine and help remove the barriers that prevent them, especially those from the black community, from achieving success and promotion within the system. Their voices are reflected in this bill, and it is my honour to bring their voices to this place.</ParaText>
              <ProceduralText TocType="TCC" id="4">(Motions deemed adopted, bill read the first time and printed)</ProceduralText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
        </SubjectOfBusinessContent>
      </SubjectOfBusiness>
      <SubjectOfBusiness id="10720886">
        <Timestamp Hr="10" Mn="15">(1015)</Timestamp>
        <FloorLanguage language="FR">[<I>Translation</I>]</FloorLanguage>
        <SubjectOfBusinessTitle> 
Parks Canada Agency Act</SubjectOfBusinessTitle>
        <SubjectOfBusinessContent>
          <Intervention Type="Debate" ToC="Yes" ToCText="Ms. Trudel" id="10720837">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="214168" Type="2">Ms. Karine Trudel (Jonquière, NDP) </Affiliation>
            </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ProceduralText TocType="TPC" id="5">Bill C-469. Introduction and first reading </ProceduralText>
              <ParaText id="6005115"> moved for leave to introduce Bill <Document DbId="10586940" Type="4">C-469, An Act to amend the Parks Canada Agency Act (Canada’s tentative list for world heritage protection)</Document>.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6005116">She said: Mr. Speaker, I am proud to rise today to introduce a bill to amend the Parks Canada Agency Act.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6005117">In 2017, the government opened Canada's tentative list for UNESCO world heritage sites to applications. Arvida, a company town, enthusiastically applied but, unfortunately, was not selected.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6005118">As an ambassador for Arvida and as a member of the House, I am proposing today that the Parks Canada Agency Act be amended so as to meet three main objectives, which are that the tentative list be reviewed every four years, that the list always include 15 sites following a review, and that the Minister of Canadian Heritage be included in the process so that the sites reflect a balance between cultural and natural sites. </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6005119">I hope that these amendments will make the process more predictable and frequent, thereby enabling the volunteers and stakeholders championing their causes, such as Arvida's, to participate more easily and effectively. I would like to give a shout-out to the Committee for the Recognition of Arvida’s Heritage Value, or CORPA, and its members for their great perseverance. We will not give up.</ParaText>
              <ProceduralText TocType="TCC" id="6">(Motions deemed adopted, bill read the first time and printed)</ProceduralText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
        </SubjectOfBusinessContent>
      </SubjectOfBusiness>
      <SubjectOfBusiness id="10720843">
        <FloorLanguage language="EN">[<I>English</I>]</FloorLanguage>
        <SubjectOfBusinessTitle>Petitions</SubjectOfBusinessTitle>
        <SubjectOfBusinessQualifier>Equalization</SubjectOfBusinessQualifier>
        <SubjectOfBusinessContent>
          <Intervention Type="Debate" ToC="Yes" ToCText="Ms. Rempel" id="10720841">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="213994" Type="2">Hon. Michelle Rempel (Calgary Nose Hill, CPC)</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="6005120">Mr. Speaker, it is my privilege to present a petition on behalf of my constituents in Calgary Nose Hill. I thank them deeply for the privilege and honour of serving them for the last four years.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6005121">The petitioners are calling on the Government of Canada to cancel Bill <Document DbId="9630600" Type="3">C-69</Document> and launch a study into the economic impact of equalization, including examining the formula; examining how renewable and non-renewable resources, including energy resources, both developed and underdeveloped, are treated in the formula; and issuing a report to Canadians on the fairness, effectiveness and outcomes of the equalization program.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
        </SubjectOfBusinessContent>
      </SubjectOfBusiness>
      <SubjectOfBusiness id="10720893">
        <SubjectOfBusinessQualifier>Environment</SubjectOfBusinessQualifier>
        <SubjectOfBusinessContent>
          <Intervention Type="Debate" ToC="Yes" ToCText="Ms. Duncan (Edmonton Strathcona)" id="10720845">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="213881" Type="2">Ms. Linda Duncan (Edmonton Strathcona, NDP)</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="6005122">Mr. Speaker, this will be my last opportunity to table a petition on behalf of my constituents.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6005123"> It is my honour to table yet another petition from my constituents calling on the government to enact a Canadian environmental bill of rights. The petitioners state that Canadians share a deep concern about the environment and recognize its inherent value; that it is important to safeguard the right of present and future generations to a healthy and ecologically balanced environment; and that it is the federal government's duty, a public trust duty, to protect the environment.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6005124">Therefore, citizens should be given the tools to hold the government accountable to protect their environment.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
        </SubjectOfBusinessContent>
      </SubjectOfBusiness>
      <SubjectOfBusiness id="10720924">
        <FloorLanguage language="FR">[<I>Translation</I>]</FloorLanguage>
        <SubjectOfBusinessQualifier>Firearms</SubjectOfBusinessQualifier>
        <SubjectOfBusinessContent>
          <Intervention Type="Debate" ToC="Yes" ToCText="Mr. Casey (Charlottetown)" id="10720847">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="213998" Type="2">Mr. Sean Casey (Charlottetown, Lib.)</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="6005125">Mr. Speaker, I rise to present a petition drafted by a group of students from Colonel Gray High School. </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6005126">A few weeks ago they invited me to talk to their class so I could explain the process of presenting a petition in the House of Commons. I have here the result of their work.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6005127">These students are studying law in their French immersion program. Their teacher is Gary Connelly, and the student who led this effort is Shaeya Thibodeau.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6005128">I want to thank and congratulate this group of young citizens who collected 781 signatures, mostly from Prince Edward Island.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6005129">The petitioners are calling on the House of Commons to pass Bill <Document DbId="9710291" Type="3">C-71</Document>, which bans military-style semi-automatic firearms in Canada, restricting the use of these weapons to military personnel only.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
        </SubjectOfBusinessContent>
      </SubjectOfBusiness>
      <SubjectOfBusiness id="10720882">
        <Timestamp Hr="10" Mn="20">(1020)</Timestamp>
        <FloorLanguage language="EN">[<I>English</I>]</FloorLanguage>
        <SubjectOfBusinessQualifier>Veterans</SubjectOfBusinessQualifier>
        <SubjectOfBusinessContent>
          <Intervention Type="Debate" ToC="Yes" ToCText="Mr. Manly" id="10720851">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="248690" Type="2">Mr. Paul Manly (Nanaimo—Ladysmith, GP)</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="6005130">Mr. Speaker, it is an honour to rise today to present four petitions on behalf of my constituents.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6005131">The first petition calls upon the <Affiliation DbId="246259" Type="4">Minister of Veterans Affairs</Affiliation> to remove any statutory limits on back-pay eligibility for the disability allowance and to work with individual veterans to achieve just and due compensation for a disability allowance in a timely manner. </ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
        </SubjectOfBusinessContent>
      </SubjectOfBusiness>
      <SubjectOfBusiness id="10720885">
        <SubjectOfBusinessQualifier>Opioids</SubjectOfBusinessQualifier>
        <SubjectOfBusinessContent>
          <Intervention Type="Debate" ToC="Yes" ToCText="Mr. Manly" id="10720884">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="248690" Type="2">Mr. Paul Manly (Nanaimo—Ladysmith, GP)</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="6005132">Mr. Speaker, the second petition calls upon the Government of Canada to cease the incarceration of those who suffer from drug abuse and to begin the rehabilitation of said victims back into society through treatment programs, as is done in Portugal.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
        </SubjectOfBusinessContent>
      </SubjectOfBusiness>
      <SubjectOfBusiness id="10720891">
        <SubjectOfBusinessQualifier>Status of Women</SubjectOfBusinessQualifier>
        <SubjectOfBusinessContent>
          <Intervention Type="Debate" ToC="Yes" ToCText="Mr. Manly" id="10720890">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="248690" Type="2">Mr. Paul Manly (Nanaimo—Ladysmith, GP)</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="6005133">Mr. Speaker, the third petition calls upon the House of Commons to recognize that violence against women remains a critical problem in Canada and disproportionately impacts indigenous women, as reflected by the crisis of missing and murdered aboriginal women; that striving for pay equity and equal participation of women in leadership roles must be political priorities for all members of Parliament; and that a shifting cultural attitude toward women and gender minorities in our society requires structural changes in education and socialization. </ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
        </SubjectOfBusinessContent>
      </SubjectOfBusiness>
      <SubjectOfBusiness id="10720897">
        <SubjectOfBusinessQualifier>National Defence</SubjectOfBusinessQualifier>
        <SubjectOfBusinessContent>
          <Intervention Type="Debate" ToC="Yes" ToCText="Mr. Manly" id="10720895">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="248690" Type="2">Mr. Paul Manly (Nanaimo—Ladysmith, GP)</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="6005134">Mr. Speaker, the final petition is from my constituents and is about DND land. The petitioners call for the Department of National Defence to clarify the safe range of the DND rifle range for safe operation; to establish a schedule for public access to the land in the buffer zone of the range; to order a feasibility study to look at relocating the range to a more suitable, less populated site; and to engage in community consultation with recreational users in the regional district of Nanaimo, the city of Nanaimo and Snuneymuxw First Nation about future use of this land.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
        </SubjectOfBusinessContent>
      </SubjectOfBusiness>
      <SubjectOfBusiness id="10720907">
        <FloorLanguage language="FR">[<I>Translation</I>]</FloorLanguage>
        <SubjectOfBusinessQualifier>Plastic Pollution</SubjectOfBusinessQualifier>
        <SubjectOfBusinessContent>
          <Intervention Type="Debate" ToC="Yes" ToCText="Mr. Godin" id="10720856">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="214107" Type="2">Mr. Joël Godin (Portneuf—Jacques-Cartier, CPC)</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="6005135">Mr. Speaker, I have two petitions to table this morning.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6005136">The first was drafted by grade-six students in Ms. Mylène Potvin's class at Harfand-des-neiges elementary school. These children showed great initiative in writing to their government. Together, they are calling on the government to curb the use of plastic bags and excess packaging.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6005137">I urge them to continue this fight. They will always be able to count on me.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
        </SubjectOfBusinessContent>
      </SubjectOfBusiness>
      <SubjectOfBusiness id="10720909">
        <SubjectOfBusinessQualifier>Telecommunications</SubjectOfBusinessQualifier>
        <SubjectOfBusinessContent>
          <Intervention Type="Debate" ToC="Yes" ToCText="Mr. Godin" id="10720908">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="214107" Type="2">Mr. Joël Godin (Portneuf—Jacques-Cartier, CPC)</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="6005138">Mr. Speaker, the second petition was prepared by the residents of the municipality of Saint-Thuribe.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6005139">They are calling on the government to provide broadband Internet so that, like all Canadians, they can have access to the modern communications of the coming decade.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6005140">I am tabling this petition in support of the residents who signed it, who are from the municipality of Saint-Thuribe, in the beautiful riding of Portneuf—Jacques-Cartier.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6005141">In closing, I would like to wish all parliamentarians, you, Mr. Speaker, support staff and the table staff a great summer. You have all made the 42nd Parliament an extraordinary one.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
        </SubjectOfBusinessContent>
      </SubjectOfBusiness>
      <SubjectOfBusiness id="10720889">
        <FloorLanguage language="EN">[<I>English</I>]</FloorLanguage>
        <SubjectOfBusinessQualifier>Pharmacare</SubjectOfBusinessQualifier>
        <SubjectOfBusinessContent>
          <Intervention Type="Debate" ToC="Yes" ToCText="Mr. Cannings" id="10720861">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="214446" Type="2">Mr. Richard Cannings (South Okanagan—West Kootenay, NDP)</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="6005142">Mr. Speaker, I rise today with two petitions from residents in my riding of South Okanagan—West Kootenay.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6005143">The first petition points out that one in 10 Canadians cannot afford their prescription medication; that the current system benefits drug companies, not Canadians; that a universal pharmacare plan could save our country over $4 billion a year; and that we are the only OECD country that has a universal health care system that does not cover prescription drugs. Therefore, the petitioners call on the Government of Canada to eliminate the current patchwork system of care and to introduce a universal, comprehensive and public pharmacare plan that will reduce drug costs and keep people healthier longer.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
        </SubjectOfBusinessContent>
      </SubjectOfBusiness>
      <SubjectOfBusiness id="10720888">
        <SubjectOfBusinessQualifier>Sinixt Nation</SubjectOfBusinessQualifier>
        <SubjectOfBusinessContent>
          <Intervention Type="Debate" ToC="Yes" ToCText="Mr. Cannings" id="10720887">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="214446" Type="2">Mr. Richard Cannings (South Okanagan—West Kootenay, NDP)</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="6005144">Mr. Speaker, the second petition draws attention to the fact that the Canadian government declared the Sinixt tribal group extinct in 1956. The petitioners also point out that the Sinixt never ceased to exist as a tribal group and that their territory remains unceded. They call on the government to reverse the wrongful declaration of the extinction of the Sinixt tribal group and to take immediate steps to recognize the Sinixt as an autonomous tribal group within their traditional and ancestral Canadian territory.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6005145">I want to take this opportunity again, since this is the last regular day of this Parliament, to thank you personally for the good job you have done in often very trying circumstances. I appreciate it, and I think all Canadians do.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Debate" ToC="No" ToCText="The Speaker" id="10720866">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="214706" Type="15">The Speaker</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="6005146">I thank the hon. member for his very kind words.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6005147">The hon. member for Cloverdale—Langley City.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
        </SubjectOfBusinessContent>
      </SubjectOfBusiness>
      <SubjectOfBusiness id="10720894">
        <SubjectOfBusinessQualifier>Burns Bog</SubjectOfBusinessQualifier>
        <SubjectOfBusinessContent>
          <Intervention Type="Debate" ToC="Yes" ToCText="Mr. Aldag" id="10720867">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="213930" Type="2">Mr. John Aldag (Cloverdale—Langley City, Lib.)</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="6005148">Mr. Speaker, I rise to table a petition concerning the Burns Bog peatland, the largest raised peatland in North America, on the west coast. It is calling on the government to protect the species at risk that are on these lands.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6005149">While I am standing, I would like to take this moment to extend my heartfelt condolences to Diane Warawa and her family and to our shared community of Langley.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6005150"> Mark was a very important person in my life. Prior to my entering politics, he was very supportive of my work and career at Parks Canada.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6005151">He did many things for our community. I know our community is going to miss him tremendously this Canada Day and beyond. It is indeed a sad day for this House and for our community.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
        </SubjectOfBusinessContent>
      </SubjectOfBusiness>
      <SubjectOfBusiness id="10720898">
        <Timestamp Hr="10" Mn="25">(1025)</Timestamp>
        <SubjectOfBusinessQualifier>Children's Rights</SubjectOfBusinessQualifier>
        <SubjectOfBusinessContent>
          <Intervention Type="Debate" ToC="Yes" ToCText="Mr. Julian" id="10720873">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="214264" Type="2">Mr. Peter Julian (New Westminster—Burnaby, NDP)</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="6005152">Mr. Speaker, it is indeed a sad day. I know that we will have an opportunity to pay tribute in an hour or two, but I too would like to pass on condolences to Diane Warawa, the children, the grandchildren and all of Mark's family. It is a very sad day for the House.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6005153">I am presenting a petition on behalf of the Elizabeth Fry Society. A few hundred Canadians are adding their names to the tens of thousands who have tabled petitions in the House so far. The petition calls on the Government of Canada to extend benefits and allowances to children who are in irregular situations. In a case where a parent is incarcerated or homeless, or the child is being raised in foster care, the children do not have the right to access the same benefits and allowances other children do. This contravenes the United Nations Convention on the Rights of the Child.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6005154">Tens of thousands of Canadians have written to Parliament in this regard. To date, the government's response has not been satisfactory. We are hoping the government will table a comprehensive response and end the discrimination so that all children can benefit from the benefits and allowances available from the federal government.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
        </SubjectOfBusinessContent>
      </SubjectOfBusiness>
      <SubjectOfBusiness id="10720876">
        <SubjectOfBusinessTitle>Questions on the Order Paper</SubjectOfBusinessTitle>
        <SubjectOfBusinessContent>
          <Intervention Type="Debate" ToC="Yes" ToCText="Mr. Lamoureux" id="10720875">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="214668" Type="18">Mr. Kevin Lamoureux (Parliamentary Secretary to the Leader of the Government in the House of Commons, Lib.)</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="6005155">Mr. Speaker, I ask that all remaining questions be allowed to stand. </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6005156">
                <B>The Speaker:</B> Is that agreed? </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6005157">
                <B>Some hon. members:</B> Agreed. </ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
        </SubjectOfBusinessContent>
      </SubjectOfBusiness>
      <SubjectOfBusiness id="10720904">
        <SubjectOfBusinessQualifier>Suspension of Sitting</SubjectOfBusinessQualifier>
        <SubjectOfBusinessContent>
          <Intervention Type="Debate" ToC="No" ToCText="The Speaker" id="10720878">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="214706" Type="15">The Speaker</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="6005158">By an order made earlier this day, the House will now stand suspended until 12 p.m.</ParaText>
              <ProceduralText TocType="TCC" id="7">(The sitting of the House was suspended at 10:27 a.m.)</ProceduralText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
        </SubjectOfBusinessContent>
      </SubjectOfBusiness>
      <SubjectOfBusiness id="10721085">
        <SubjectOfBusinessQualifier>Sitting Resumed</SubjectOfBusinessQualifier>
        <SubjectOfBusinessContent>
          <ProceduralText TocType="TCC" id="8">(The House resumed at 12:04 p.m.)</ProceduralText>
        </SubjectOfBusinessContent>
      </SubjectOfBusiness>
      <SubjectOfBusiness id="10721065">
        <Timestamp Hr="12" Mn="00">(1200)</Timestamp>
        <SubjectOfBusinessTitle>Mark Warawa</SubjectOfBusinessTitle>
        <CatchLine>Tributes</CatchLine>
        <SubjectOfBusinessContent>
          <Intervention Type="Debate" ToC="No" ToCText="The Speaker" id="10721066">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="214706" Type="15">The Speaker</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="6005159">My dear colleagues, there have been discussions among members of the parties in the House, and I understand that we will now proceed to tributes to our late colleague, Mark Warawa.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6005160">I now recognize the member for Abbotsford.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Timestamp Hr="12" Mn="05">(1205)</Timestamp>
          <Intervention Type="Debate" ToC="Yes" ToCText="Mr. Fast" id="10721068">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="214072" Type="2">Hon. Ed Fast (Abbotsford, CPC)</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="6005161">Mr. Speaker, my dear friend, our dear friend, Mark Warawa, died this morning. He passed away after a brief but valiant battle against cancer. He died peacefully, with his loving wife, Diane, by his side at Langley Hospice.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6005162">Members will know that Mark announced his retirement from politics in January of this year, well before his cancer diagnosis in April. He had planned, in his retirement, to continue a community service as chaplain to seniors, something that was very close to his heart. By the way, he was not going to be paid for that service; he was just going to contribute back to his community. Sadly, he did not live long enough to embark upon that new adventure.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6005163">On May 7, Mark found enough strength to deliver his farewell speech in this House, which was received with a standing ovation and many tears from his fellow MPs from every party in the House. On May 21, Mark made his last public appearance, waving from his car and greeting well-wishers at the Fort Langley May Day Parade.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6005164">For those who do not know, Mark began his public life as an Abbotsford city councillor, serving for 14 years under the tutelage of George Ferguson, Abbotsford's legendary and longest-serving mayor. Mark and I served on city council together. Along with former councillor Simon Gibson, we were called the three horsemen, because of our tendency to vote the same way on many issues. Mark and I thoroughly enjoyed our time on council, and we became lifelong friends, as did our wives, Annette and Diane. </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6005165">Mark then moved to federal politics, winning the election as a Conservative candidate for the newly formed electoral district of Langley back in June 2004. He was re-elected five times, the last time in October 2015.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6005166"> As MPs, we love to socialize together. What the public sees in this House is actually quite different from what happens outside of this House. We are all colleagues; we are all friends, and a lot of us socialize together. </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6005167">On our side, there were five of us who called ourselves the MP5. We are all very interested in music and singing gospel music. As I mentioned in my earlier comments, the MP5 had the chance to sing at the National Arts Centre. That went okay, but members should know that of all our repertoire, there was one song that was Mark's favourite, and it began with the line, “I woke up this morning feeling fine.” This morning, Mark Warawa woke up feeling extra fine.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6005168">Mark loved this place and what this place represents, the heart of our democracy and the place where serious national issues are debated without fear of recrimination. He also loved his MP colleagues and respected the role we all play in defending a free and democratic society. Indeed, he loved to promote these values around the world. It was actually only a few months ago that Mark, as a Ukrainian Canadian, served as an official election monitor in the Ukrainian elections. Sadly, he had to return to Canada early because of his illness. </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6005169">I know he was dearly loved by those who work in this House. In fact, if there was an award for the kindest MP in the House, I am guessing he would have won that award. However, if we had asked Mark what the most important thing in his life was, he would have said it was his deep and abiding faith in God's providence and hand on his life.</ParaText>
              <Timestamp Hr="12" Mn="10">(1210)</Timestamp>
              <ParaText id="6005170">Mark embraced his journey with cancer as he did most things, with dignity and grace, with courage and hope, with an open heart and lots of prayer. He was a passionate Christ follower and loved Jesus with all his heart and soul. That is what he would have wanted us to have known and remembered him for.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6005171">Mark was a devoted husband to his wife of 46 years, Diane, and father to their five children: Jonathan, Ryan, Nathan, Eric and Kristen. He was a grandparent as well to 10 grandchildren. Together we grieve with all of them, but not as those without hope. Mark knew where he was going and what his final glorious destination would be.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6005172">To all of the Warawa family, we say thank you. You shared Mark with us for so many years. Thank you for his service to Canada and for his commitment to promoting the values that all of us hold so dear. </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6005173">Mark will be missed, but I know he is rejoicing in the presence of his Lord and Saviour, Jesus Christ.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6005174">Mark, from all of us in the House, especially from your Conservative family, Godspeed, till we meet again.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Debate" ToC="Yes" ToCText="Mr. Aldag" id="10721074">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="213930" Type="2">Mr. John Aldag (Cloverdale—Langley City, Lib.)</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="6005175">Mr. Speaker, I was deeply saddened to learn this morning of the passing of our colleague in this House, Mark Warawa, a man who proudly represented his constituency of <Affiliation DbId="213926" Type="2">Langley—Aldergrove</Affiliation> this term and the communities of the Township of Langley and Langley City, or “the Langleys” as we call them locally, since 2004.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6005176">I met Mark and his wife Diane shortly after my wife and I moved with our family to the Township of Langley in 2005. I was a manager with Parks Canada based at Fort Langley National Historic Site. Mark loved participating in special events at the fort, fondly known as the birthplace of B.C. </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6005177">Mark embraced the roots of our community and commissioned a period gentleman's outfit to wear at special events, including the community's May Day celebrations, Canada Day, Douglas Day and other events. The community always looked forward to Mark's Canada Day cupcakes, which he proudly served each and every Canada Day.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6005178">Mark loved participating in citizenship ceremonies at the fort, sharing the story of his family's journey to Canada and the opportunities that our rich land gave them, including to Mark personally, and his ability to serve in office on behalf of his constituents.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6005179">Mark was a huge supporter of the fort and attended every event possible. I got to know him and his love for our community through almost a decade of working together in a non-partisan fashion. I respected Mark deeply for his caring manner. Mark and his wife Diane were at as many community events as possible, and I always enjoyed encountering both of them around the Langleys. </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6005180">On a family trip to Ottawa several years back, Mark insisted on touring my family around Parliament Hill. He staged mock media interviews with my three children. He introduced us to the excellent staff in the dining room. He proudly shared this place, and the honour it is to serve, with my family. The look in his eyes, of excitement, honour and humility, is a look I will always remember, and one that I have tried to emulate during my time in this chamber.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6005181">For the 2015 election, the Langleys were divided into two new ridings. I was elected to represent Cloverdale—Langley City. Upon my taking office, Mark reached out and helped my team get up and running. There were cases from before the election that Mark knew, and he helped my team resolve these files. He provided valuable advice to me on setting up offices in Ottawa and at home. He was a huge mentor in those early days.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6005182">We were able to serve together on the Special Joint Committee on Physician-Assisted Dying as well as the Standing Committee on Environment and Sustainable Development. </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6005183">I admired Mark's deep commitment to his personal beliefs and his faith. His trust in his Lord and God provided him much strength during his brief but valiant fight with cancer.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6005184">On behalf of the <Affiliation DbId="214296" Type="1">Prime Minister</Affiliation>, the government and all my Liberal colleagues, I offer our deepest condolences to Mark's family, to his wife Diane and his five children, Jonathan, Ryan, Nathan, Eric and Kristen, to their spouses and Mark's 10 grandchildren, of whom he was so fiercely proud, as well as to Mark's entire Conservative family.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6005185">Thank you to Mark's family and to the residents of the Langleys for having shared Mark with Canada over these past 15 years. Mark will be missed.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Timestamp Hr="12" Mn="15">(1215)</Timestamp>
          <Intervention Type="Debate" ToC="Yes" ToCText="Mr. Cullen" id="10721080">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="214590" Type="2">Mr. Nathan Cullen (Skeena—Bulkley Valley, NDP)</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="6005186">Mr. Speaker, today I rise to join colleagues in paying tribute to a friend and colleague, Mark Warawa. I think all of us agree that we would have given anything to be talking about something else here today than Mark's passing.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6005187">It is such a tribute to Mark that there are so many of us here today, choosing not to head home to our own families, and that all parties are here, and independents, regardless of whether we often or even ever agreed with Mark on his politics and policies. I am including my Conservative colleagues in that. He was a man of such deep faith and conviction, and he held those convictions with such a degree of grace and certainty, which is sometimes too rare in our world.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6005188">Today was meant to be a day of ending, as we conclude this Parliament, as we reflect as parliamentarians on our time here, be it these past four years or for some of us many more years. It is also a day, by bad circumstance, that we are talking about a different kind of ending.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6005189">It is a privilege to stand in this place. Mark always saw that to be true for him, so much so that even as he was so sick, he was determined to come back and give his farewell address to the House, despite his doctors not necessarily agreeing with that.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6005190">I am honoured to speak on behalf of my New Democratic colleagues. Mark was an opponent, yet never an enemy. Our friendship was most unlikely. We come from different generations and opposite ends of the political spectrum on almost every issue, yet we found some common ground in the humanity we could share in this place. I think I can speak for many colleagues who also saw that humanity on display.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6005191">I do have to tell one story, though. I was reflecting this morning about one day when, in the heat of debate, I said something that really upset Mark. I honestly do not remember what it was. I guess I have one of those memories.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6005192"> Mark came right up to me in my seat. He got right in my face and was really mad, almost on the edge of asking me to step outside. I was a bit shocked. It seemed out of character for him, yet, within minutes, he was back at my desk, apologizing and wanting to make things right. It is important to consider that I do not remember what we were arguing about, but I do remember the apology. I remember the humanity.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6005193">For him, I think politics was very personal, but he never made it personal, and that is a rare gift.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6005194">I was raised in the church. I do not claim to know definitively what a good Christian is, but Mark strove in every way to be one. </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6005195">I also think we are talking a lot about family today, political family and Mark's family, Diane, Jonathan, Ryan, Nathan, Eric and Kristen. There are families we are born into and there are families we choose.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6005196"> Diane and Mark were married for just a little less time than I have been alive. Mark, in his final comments to me, said, “I always thought of you as a son”, again, curious and somewhat unlikely, our friendship.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6005197">Today is about an ending. It is about mourning and it is about honouring. I join my colleagues and friends in honouring the memory of Mark, and I wish Diane and his entire family the very best and peace.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <FloorLanguage language="FR">[<I>Translation</I>]</FloorLanguage>
          <Intervention Type="Debate" ToC="Yes" ToCText="Mr. Thériault" id="10721092">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="214205" Type="2">Mr. Luc Thériault (Montcalm, BQ)</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="6005198">Mr. Speaker, on behalf of the Bloc Québécois, I would like to offer my condolences to Mr. Warawa's family and friends and to his colleagues in the Conservative caucus.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6005199">Mr. Warawa proudly served the people of Langley—Aldergrove for 15 years. He was taken from us by cancer today, reminding us that there is still a long way to go to beat this terrible disease.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6005200">The last time he addressed the House, Mr. Warawa knew this day would come. He reminded us that members must not let themselves get too caught up in politics and forget what matters. He told us to take care of ourselves and to spend time with our families, because in the end, that is what really matters.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6005201">Rest in peace, Mark. Thank you for your public service and your contribution to your country.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Timestamp Hr="12" Mn="20">(1220)</Timestamp>
          <FloorLanguage language="EN">[<I>English</I>]</FloorLanguage>
          <Intervention Type="Debate" ToC="Yes" ToCText="Ms. May (Saanich—Gulf Islands)" id="10721096">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="214382" Type="2">Ms. Elizabeth May (Saanich—Gulf Islands, GP)</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="6005202">Mr. Speaker and dear friends, the hon. member for <Affiliation DbId="213926" Type="2">Langley—Aldergrove</Affiliation> can now be addressed by his real name, because he has passed from us.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6005203">Mark Warawa was a dear friend of mine, and I want to identify some things about my experience of knowing Mark, in expressing my deep condolences to Diane.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6005204">One thing I noticed right away about Mark is that it was Mark and Diane. There is a plane that leaves Vancouver to bring B.C. MPs to Ottawa every week, and sometimes I call it the school bus. If there was a spouse who was almost always there, it was Diane. I think she travelled to Ottawa with Mark more often than most.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6005205">I know how hard this is right now. As we know, Mark is in the arms of our Lord, and it is Diane to whom we send our prayers and deepest condolences, so she may have strength in this difficult time.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6005206">This is how I knew Mark. I was elected to this place in 2011. From 2006 to 2011, before I was elected, Mark Warawa had the title of Parliamentary Secretary to the Minister of Environment. I worked with him often. I talked to him often. Although we did not agree on policy, his personal commitments were clear. He and Diane had done many things in their own home: They had solar panels; they composted. He could go on and on. He really was committed to doing things in his own life to make this a better world.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6005207">He also created a local award in Langley for environmental heroes. It mattered to him. He did things in his own way. He never would have thwarted policies of his own party; I am not suggesting that at all. He was committed, and he took the time to talk to me and, as we have heard, always in respectful ways.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6005208">When I was elected, I got to know Mark in a whole new way. I hope Canadians will be happy to know such a thing exists, as we do not talk about it very much here, but the one truly non-partisan thing that happens in this place, every single Wednesday at 7 a.m., is that we gather in prayer. My brother from <Affiliation DbId="214488" Type="2">Battle River—Crowfoot</Affiliation> looks at me and I am going to start crying. It keeps me going, goodness knows, to know that despite the fact that we may not agree on anything, we are able to love each other.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6005209">I loved Mark. He was so clear, focused and devoted to the Lord in his day-to-day life and, as we have heard from other members from other parties, in how he conducted himself in this place.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6005210">He had real courage. One thing we have talked about lately at the procedure and House affairs committee is how to reduce the role of the party whips in controlling what happens here. A lot of people talk about it, but in my eight years of experience, Mark Warawa was the bravest in standing up against a party whip. He told us that when he was going to give his Standing Order 31 statement, he was told by the whip he was not allowed to bring it forward. At the time, the Speaker ruled on that. Eleven other members of Parliament, including many members of Mark's party, stood up to agree with him.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6005211">I just want it remembered that Mark stood up for democracy in this place, when he could have been afraid, when he could have taken the easy route and not thwarted his party whip. He had confidence in the right of all members of Parliament in this place to speak to what was in their hearts and say what they wanted to say in their own 60-second opportunity every few months. He stood up on principle and asked for the Speaker to rule that his rights had been violated. That was brave.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6005212">Of many things about Mark Warawa's life, he will be remembered. As we heard from the member for <Affiliation DbId="214072" Type="2">Abbotsford</Affiliation>, he was a community champion, working at the local level and municipal government before coming to this place. As the member for <Affiliation DbId="214590" Type="2">Skeena—Bulkley Valley</Affiliation> so rightly said, he was someone known for his kindness. I also want him remembered for his willingness to reach across party lines.</ParaText>
              <Timestamp Hr="12" Mn="25">(1225)</Timestamp>
              <ParaText id="6005213"> There was a moment, and this is my last story, when a student from Langley contacted me. He was on an adventure in citizenship program. He said that he was supposed to have lunch with his own MP, but since he was not a Conservative, he wanted to meet me. I said to him, “Your MP is a great guy. I think you should have lunch with both of us.” I asked Mark, and he said, “Absolutely, let's both take our student to lunch.”</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6005214">We had this wonderful, wide-ranging conversation about environmental goals. I could see this young high school student's eyes light up because he realized he did not have to be a Conservative to love his MP. He just had to know him and know that he really was doing the best he could by his own lights every day. Then, in a truly generous gesture, Mark picked up the tab. That does not happen every day, around here or anywhere.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6005215">God bless you, Mark. God, greet one of your wonderful spirits, a soul who has served you well. Give him eternal rest. Let light perpetual shine upon him. Thank you, Lord, that we came to know him and call him friend.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Debate" ToC="Yes" ToCText="The Speaker" id="10721109">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="214706" Type="15">The Speaker</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="6005216">I want to thank the hon. members for <Affiliation DbId="214072" Type="2">Abbotsford</Affiliation>, <Affiliation DbId="213930" Type="2">Cloverdale—Langley City</Affiliation>, <Affiliation DbId="214590" Type="2">Skeena—Bulkley Valley</Affiliation>, <Affiliation DbId="214205" Type="2">Montcalm</Affiliation> and <Affiliation DbId="214382" Type="2">Saanich—Gulf Islands</Affiliation> for their very eloquent comments, to which I think we all want to attach ourselves.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6005217">Mark Warawa will be missed by all of us. He was a dedicated member of Parliament whose constituents' faith in him returned him to the House an impressive five times. Even more important, he was a good and kind man.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6005218"> I knew him for many years. We served together on the Standing Committee on Natural Resources. We would often chat when walking back and forth between the House and committee. In all the years I knew him, whether it was privately or in the House or in committee, I never once heard him speak to or about anyone with malice.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6005219">He spoke here of course on May 7, his last appearance in the House, and it seems like only moments ago. He spoke with calm and serene confidence and courage. He still had some hope that maybe there would be a solution for him, something that would overcome this problem with cancer, but he also knew what might lie ahead and he faced it with serenity and courage.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6005220"> He spoke about his work as a member of Parliament, his love for this place and love for his constituents. He spoke, of course, about his wife Diane and his love for her and for his children and grandchildren, to whom we all offer our condolences. Those people meant a lot to him, as I know his constituents did.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6005221">Colleagues, if we are all the poorer for his passing, we are the richer for having known him.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6005222">I invite all hon. members to stand to observe a moment of silence in honour of our dear colleague Mark Warawa.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6005223">[<I>A moment of silence observed</I>]</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
        </SubjectOfBusinessContent>
      </SubjectOfBusiness>
      <SubjectOfBusiness id="10721118">
        <Timestamp Hr="12" Mn="30">(1230)</Timestamp>
        <SubjectOfBusinessTitle>Business of the House</SubjectOfBusinessTitle>
        <SubjectOfBusinessContent>
          <Intervention Type="Debate" ToC="Yes" ToCText="Ms. Chagger" id="10721119">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="224669" Type="4">Hon. Bardish Chagger (Leader of the Government in the House of Commons, Lib.)</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="6005224">Mr. Speaker, there have been discussions among the parties and if you seek it, I think you will find unanimous consent for the following motion:</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6005225">
                <Quote>
                  <QuotePara Align="Left" IndentFirst="2" IndentRest="1">That, notwithstanding any Standing or Special Order or usual practice of the House: </QuotePara>
                </Quote>
              </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6005226">
                <Quote>
                  <QuotePara IndentFirst="2" IndentRest="2">(a) the amendment to the motion respecting the senate amendments to Bill <Document DbId="10078426" Type="3">C-83, An Act to amend the Corrections and Conditional Release Act and another Act</Document>, be deemed negatived on division and the main motion be deemed carried on division; and</QuotePara>
                </Quote>
              </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6005227">
                <Quote>
                  <QuotePara IndentFirst="2" IndentRest="2">(b) the amendment to the motion for second reading of Bill <Document DbId="10511099" Type="3">C-100, An Act to implement the Agreement between Canada, the United States of America and the United Mexican States</Document>, be deemed negatived on division and that the Bill be deemed read a second time and referred to the Standing Committee on International Trade.</QuotePara>
                </Quote>
              </ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Debate" ToC="No" ToCText="The Speaker" id="10721120">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="214706" Type="15">The Speaker</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="6005228">Does the hon. government House leader have the unanimous consent of the House to propose the motion?</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6005229">
                <B>Some hon. members:</B> Agreed.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6005230">
                <B>The Speaker:</B> The House has heard the terms of the motion. Is it the pleasure of the House to adopt the motion?</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6005231">
                <B>Some hon. members:</B> Agreed.</ParaText>
              <ProceduralText TocType="TCC" id="9">(Motion agreed to)</ProceduralText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
        </SubjectOfBusinessContent>
      </SubjectOfBusiness>
      <SubjectOfBusiness id="10721143">
        <SubjectOfBusinessTitle>Corrections and Conditional Release Act</SubjectOfBusinessTitle>
        <ProceduralText TocType="TCC" id="10">(Bill C-83. On the Order: Government Orders:)</ProceduralText>
        <SubjectOfBusinessContent>
          <ParaText id="6005232">
            <Quote>
              <QuotePara Align="Left" IndentFirst="2" IndentRest="1"> June 19, 2019—The Minister of Public Safety and Emergency Preparedness—Resuming consideration of the amendments made by the Senate to Bill C-83, An Act to amend the Corrections and Conditional Release Act and another Act.</QuotePara>
            </Quote>
          </ParaText>
          <ProceduralText TocType="TCC" id="11">(Amendment negatived on division and the main motion agreed to on division)</ProceduralText>
        </SubjectOfBusinessContent>
      </SubjectOfBusiness>
      <SubjectOfBusiness id="10721155">
        <SubjectOfBusinessTitle>Canada-United States-Mexico Agreement Implementation Act</SubjectOfBusinessTitle>
        <CatchLine>Government Orders</CatchLine>
        <ProceduralText TocType="TCC" id="12">(Bill C-100. On the Order: Government Orders)</ProceduralText>
        <SubjectOfBusinessContent>
          <ParaText id="6005233">
            <Quote>
              <QuotePara Align="Left" IndentFirst="2" IndentRest="1"> June 19, 2019—Resuming consideration of the motion of Mr. Trudeau (Prime Minister), seconded by Ms. Chagger (Leader of the Government in the House of Commons), —That Bill C-100, An Act to implement the Agreement between Canada, the United States of America and the United Mexican States, be now read a second time and referred to the Standing Committee on International Trade.</QuotePara>
            </Quote>
          </ParaText>
          <ParaText id="6005234">
            <Quote>
              <QuotePara Align="Left" IndentFirst="2" IndentRest="1"> Deferred recorded division on the amendment of Ms. Hardcastle (Windsor—Tecumseh), seconded by Mr. Masse (Windsor West), —That the motion be amended by deleting all the words after the word “That” and substituting the following: </QuotePara>
            </Quote>
          </ParaText>
          <ParaText id="6005235">
            <Quote>
              <QuotePara Align="Left" IndentFirst="2" IndentRest="2">“the House decline to give second reading to Bill C-100, An Act to implement the Agreement between Canada, the United States of America and the United Mexican States, because it:</QuotePara>
            </Quote>
          </ParaText>
          <ParaText id="6005236">
            <Quote>
              <QuotePara Align="Left" IndentFirst="2" IndentRest="2">(a) fails to improve labour provisions that are necessary to protect good jobs;</QuotePara>
            </Quote>
          </ParaText>
          <ParaText id="6005237">
            <Quote>
              <QuotePara Align="Left" IndentFirst="2" IndentRest="2">(b) allows for an extension of drug patents that will significantly increase the cost of medicine for Canadians;</QuotePara>
            </Quote>
          </ParaText>
          <ParaText id="6005238">
            <Quote>
              <QuotePara Align="Left" IndentFirst="2" IndentRest="2">(c) leaves the environment vulnerable due to the absence of clear, enforceable protection provisions; </QuotePara>
            </Quote>
          </ParaText>
          <ParaText id="6005239">
            <Quote>
              <QuotePara Align="Left" IndentFirst="2" IndentRest="2">(d) is being rushed through the legislative process, without adequate time and attention for such a crucial trade agreement; </QuotePara>
            </Quote>
          </ParaText>
          <ParaText id="6005240">
            <Quote>
              <QuotePara Align="Left" IndentFirst="2" IndentRest="2">(e) will shift the levers of power within the economy away from governments and workers, in favour of corporations, by weakening public regulations on public health and the environment; </QuotePara>
            </Quote>
          </ParaText>
          <ParaText id="6005241">
            <Quote>
              <QuotePara Align="Left" IndentFirst="2" IndentRest="2">and
(f) puts the poorest and most marginalized Canadians at further risk by failing to ensure the protection of human rights, gender equality and inclusive economic growth.”.
</QuotePara>
            </Quote>
          </ParaText>
          <ProceduralText TocType="TCC" id="13">(Amendment negatived on division, bill read a second time on division and referred to a committee)</ProceduralText>
          <Intervention Type="Debate" ToC="Yes" ToCText="Ms. Chagger" id="10721121">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="224669" Type="4">Hon. Bardish Chagger (Leader of the Government in the House of Commons, Lib.)</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="6005242">Mr. Speaker, there is something about this place when there are flowers on a desk. It is just a heavy place to be in. I want my Conservative colleagues to know that our thoughts are definitely with them.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6005243">I also want to take a moment to say that it takes many people to support us in doing the work we do. Whether it is the people who clean for us, the people who feed us or the people who support us and allow us to do the important work we do, I would like to, on behalf of all members, thank them.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6005244">I would like to thank the House administration and the pages. I would also like to thank and acknowledge the families and loved ones who allow us to do the work we do and allow the people who support us to do the work they do. They often go unnoticed and are not always appreciated, but we sincerely appreciate all their efforts.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6005245">I also want to thank the House leadership teams, from all parties, that have worked together, including the whips' desks. They are here with us to support us, and they work very hard. They do not put their names on a ballot, but they sure do allow us to serve on behalf of democracy.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6005246">I wish all members a safe, enjoyable and healthy summer. I want to see everyone back here. I want them to be successful in all their endeavours. I know that many colleagues are going through challenges, and I want them all to know that they are in our thoughts and prayers. We wish everyone well with all their endeavours. </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6005247">Therefore, out of respect for the memory of our late colleague, Mark Warawa, I move, seconded by the member for <Affiliation DbId="214460" Type="2">Portage—Lisgar</Affiliation>: </ParaText>
              <ProceduralText TocType="TPC" id="14">Motion</ProceduralText>
              <ParaText id="6005248">
                <Quote>
                  <QuotePara Align="Left" IndentFirst="2" IndentRest="1">That the House do now adjourn.</QuotePara>
                </Quote>
              </ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Debate" ToC="No" ToCText="The Speaker" id="10721123">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="214706" Type="15">The Speaker</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="6005249">May I first attach myself to the comments about our appreciation for all the staff in this place. I do not like to start listing them all, because I might miss some, but a couple come to mind, and that would be the people who do cleaning for us. When some of us come here very early in the morning, we find them finishing their work that they have been doing overnight. There are those who move furniture around. There are many others, so many others. There are the interpreters, and so many others. I have started to list, but I had better stop. There are so many who do such great work for us.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6005250">The question is on the motion. Is it the pleasure of the House to adopt the motion?</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6005252">
                <B>Some hon. members:</B> Agreed. </ParaText>
              <ProceduralText TocType="TCC" id="15">(Motion carried)</ProceduralText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Timestamp Hr="12" Mn="35">(1235)</Timestamp>
          <Intervention Type="Debate" ToC="No" ToCText="The Speaker" id="10721125">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="214706" Type="15">The Speaker</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="6005253">Accordingly, pursuant to an order made Wednesday, June 19, the House stands adjourned until Monday, September 16, 2019, at <?bk ?>11 a.m.<?ek ?>, pursuant to <?bk ?>Standing Orders 28(2)<?ek ?> and <?bk ?>24(1)<?ek ?>.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6005254">(The House adjourned at 12:35 p.m.)</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
        </SubjectOfBusinessContent>
      </SubjectOfBusiness>
    </OrderOfBusiness>
  </HansardBody>
</Hansard>