<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Hansard xml:lang="EN" id="10814026">
  <StartPageNumber>2061</StartPageNumber>
  <DocumentTitle>
    <DocumentName>OFFICIAL REPORT (HANSARD)</DocumentName>
  </DocumentTitle>
  <ExtractedInformation>
    <ExtractedItem Name="InstitutionDebate">House of Commons Debates</ExtractedItem>
    <ExtractedItem Name="Volume">Volume 149</ExtractedItem>
    <ExtractedItem Name="Number">No. 031</ExtractedItem>
    <ExtractedItem Name="Session">1st SESSION</ExtractedItem>
    <ExtractedItem Name="Parliament">43rd PARLIAMENT</ExtractedItem>
    <ExtractedItem Name="Date">Friday, March 13, 2020</ExtractedItem>
    <ExtractedItem Name="SpeakerName">Speaker: The Honourable Anthony Rota</ExtractedItem>
    <ExtractedItem Name="Institution">HOUSE OF COMMONS</ExtractedItem>
    <ExtractedItem Name="Country">CANADA</ExtractedItem>
    <ExtractedItem Name="TOCNote">(Table of Contents appears at back of this issue.)</ExtractedItem>
    <ExtractedItem Name="HeaderTitle">COMMONS DEBATES</ExtractedItem>
    <ExtractedItem Name="HeaderDate">March 13, 2020</ExtractedItem>
    <ExtractedItem Name="MetaDocumentCategory">DEBATES</ExtractedItem>
    <ExtractedItem Name="MetaTitle">No. 031</ExtractedItem>
    <ExtractedItem Name="MetaTitleEn">No. 031</ExtractedItem>
    <ExtractedItem Name="MetaTitleFr">N<Sup>o</Sup> 031</ExtractedItem>
    <ExtractedItem Name="MetaVolumeNumber">Volume 149</ExtractedItem>
    <ExtractedItem Name="MetaNumberNumber">031</ExtractedItem>
    <ExtractedItem Name="MetaDateNumDay">13</ExtractedItem>
    <ExtractedItem Name="MetaDateNumMonth">03</ExtractedItem>
    <ExtractedItem Name="MetaDateNumYear">2020</ExtractedItem>
    <ExtractedItem Name="MetaCreationTime">2020/03/13 10:05:00</ExtractedItem>
    <ExtractedItem Name="InstitutionDebateFr">Débats de la Chambre des communes</ExtractedItem>
    <ExtractedItem Name="InstitutionDebateEn">House of Commons Debates</ExtractedItem>
    <ExtractedItem Name="MetaInstitution">House Of Commons</ExtractedItem>
    <ExtractedItem Name="SessionNumber">1</ExtractedItem>
    <ExtractedItem Name="ParliamentNumber">43</ExtractedItem>
    <ExtractedItem Name="InCameraNote">
    </ExtractedItem>
  </ExtractedInformation>
  <HansardBody>
    <Intro>
      <ParaText id="6099340">The House met at 10 a.m.</ParaText>
      <Prayer>Prayer</Prayer>
      <Timestamp Hr="10" Mn="05">(1005)</Timestamp>
      <FloorLanguage language="EN">[<I>English</I>]</FloorLanguage>
      <Intervention Type="Debate" ToC="No" ToCText="Mrs. Mendès" id="10814029">
        <PersonSpeaking>
          <Affiliation DbId="253712" Type="93">The Assistant Deputy Speaker (Mrs. Alexandra Mendès)</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
        <Content>
          <ParaText id="6099341">I understand that there is an agreement between the parties to have some brief statements.</ParaText>
        </Content>
      </Intervention>
      <SubjectOfBusiness id="10814031">
        <SubjectOfBusinessTitle>Business of the House</SubjectOfBusinessTitle>
        <SubjectOfBusinessQualifier>Statements Regarding COVID-19</SubjectOfBusinessQualifier>
        <CatchLine>Business of the House</CatchLine>
        <SubjectOfBusinessContent>
          <Intervention Type="Statement" ToC="Yes" ToCText="Mr. Strahl" id="10814030">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="252755" Type="2">Mr. Mark Strahl (Chilliwack—Hope, CPC)</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="6099342">Madam Speaker, I rise today on behalf of the official opposition to offer my thoughts and prayers to the <Affiliation DbId="214296" Type="1">Prime Minister</Affiliation>, his wife, all parliamentarians and indeed all Canadians who are experiencing or know someone affected by COVID-19.</ParaText>
              <FloorLanguage language="FR">[<I>Translation</I>]</FloorLanguage>
              <ParaText id="6099343"> I would also like to thank all public health officials and front-line health care workers who are working around the clock to keep Canadians healthy and safe.</ParaText>
              <FloorLanguage language="EN">[<I>English</I>]</FloorLanguage>
              <ParaText id="6099344">These are extraordinary times. With the World Health Organization declaring COVID-19 a global pandemic, it is incumbent on everyone to exercise the highest degree of caution. My colleagues and I, in direct collaboration with our friends across the aisle, have come to an arrangement to suspend Parliament while ensuring the government continues to have the authority and capability to provide our country with necessary financial supports.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6099345">There continue to remain significant questions about the Government of Canada's management of this pandemic. While we understand that COVID-19 does not respect borders, the government can consider measures to further contain the virus from spreading, such as more vigorous screening upon entry, mandatory quarantine for those who enter from high-risk countries and potentially stopping incoming and outgoing flights from high-risk areas. The government's relying on Canadians to have enough supplies to weather the pandemic is simply not enough.</ParaText>
              <FloorLanguage language="FR">[<I>Translation</I>]</FloorLanguage>
              <ParaText id="6099346"> Canadians need to be reassured that the government is prepared to assist and support those affected by the coronavirus. We also need to see a comprehensive plan to protect the health and safety of all Canadians.</ParaText>
              <FloorLanguage language="EN">[<I>English</I>]</FloorLanguage>
              <ParaText id="6099347">We as the official opposition will continue to do our elected duties outside of the confines of Parliament and will continue to press the government for the answers Canadians deserve.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6099348">Stay healthy. God bless you all, and God bless Canada.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <FloorLanguage language="FR">[<I>Translation</I>]</FloorLanguage>
          <Intervention Type="Debate" ToC="Yes" ToCText="Mr. Blanchet" id="10814036">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="252623" Type="2">Mr. Yves-François Blanchet (Beloeil—Chambly, BQ)</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="6099349">Madam Speaker, the motion I want to speak to has not been formally moved yet. I am not sure what that means from a procedural standpoint. I will proceed and the House can decide thereafter. </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6099350">To all Quebeckers back home concerned about the spread of a virus that may, in some cases, be life-threatening, I wish them courage.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6099351">I wish a speedy recovery to all those who will get sick in the coming weeks, including, of course, the <Affiliation DbId="214296" Type="1">Prime Minister</Affiliation>'s wife.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6099352">It is also my wish that we deal with this challenge before us swiftly, wisely and carefully. I ask that we restrain our propensity for playing politics and instead become protectors of the common good. That is what the Bloc Québécois will do.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6099353">Nevertheless, the suspension of Parliament should not mean and will not mean that the Bloc Québécois will be less present or less vigilant with regard to anything that might be detrimental to the interests of Quebec. The Bloc will continue to offer proposals to better serve those interests.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6099354">In light of how vigorously and quickly the coronavirus is spreading, numerous possible responses have been proposed. Time will tell which responses were appropriate. We will have to learn from this experience.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6099355">One thing that seems to have been handled poorly and inconsistently is border crossings: protocols, equipment, training, detection, referrals, quarantine and, in some cases, some level of shutdown.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6099356"> If it cannot be avoided, accelerating an economic slowdown—I realize that is an oxymoron—recession or crisis is a cure that is worse than the disease in some ways. History has also taught us that the earliest victims of a crisis are the most vulnerable members of society.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6099357">Members can see why the Bloc Québécois is pushing for major accommodations in the employment insurance system and for changes that give seniors in the regions more purchasing power as soon as possible. Parliament may not be sitting, but the Bloc Québécois will be watching closely and speaking up. We were elected to be here and stand up for our people. We understand why this has to happen, we accept it, and we were part of the conversation that led to this morning's motion. However, we will insist that lost sitting days be made up, especially given the minority government context.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6099358">The coronavirus pandemic will leave an indelible mark on our planet, on Quebec and on Canada. Our response to the pandemic will also have a long-lasting economic impact. Let us therefore choose wisely.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6099359">Finally, it is important that compassion be the main principle guiding our decisions and actions. I remain committed to working to mitigate, as much as possible, the impact and suffering this crisis might have on Quebeckers.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Debate" ToC="Yes" ToCText="Mr. Julian" id="10814039">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="252953" Type="2">Mr. Peter Julian (New Westminster—Burnaby, NDP)</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="6099360">Madam Speaker, today our thoughts are with Ms. Grégoire and the 155 other Canadians across the country who have contracted the coronavirus.</ParaText>
              <FloorLanguage language="EN">[<I>English</I>]</FloorLanguage>
              <ParaText id="6099361">In this place, Canadians often see how our parties differ, and the differences we have. They see the questions we ask each other in question period. What Canadians often see is the variety of opinions within this House of Commons.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6099362">Today, however, we see all parties and all members of Parliament coming together with the same mission. That mission is to confront the challenge of coronavirus in Canada and to do our part to minimize the dangers of this virus going further in the public sphere.</ParaText>
              <FloorLanguage language="FR">[<I>Translation</I>]</FloorLanguage>
              <ParaText id="6099363">Unanimity is rare, but it is important when we face a challenge that affects all of Canada. It is important that members come together and confirm that we will work collaboratively.</ParaText>
              <FloorLanguage language="EN">[<I>English</I>]</FloorLanguage>
              <ParaText id="6099364">Canadians come together when there are challenges. That has always been the hallmark of our character. Today, as we know, public health officials told us that it is important for members of Parliament, like everyone else in Canada, to maintain the social distancing that is so important to assure we do not see a rapid multiplication of the virus.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6099365">Our health officers across the country, and I would like to give a shout-out to Dr. Bonnie Henry from British Columbia, have been tirelessly working to ensure Canadians understand the implications of not having that social distancing. The reality of our parliamentary life is that we travel across the country. If we did not take this hiatus, we could have members of Parliament bringing the virus back to Ottawa, or taking the virus from Ottawa to their home constituencies.</ParaText>
              <FloorLanguage language="FR">[<I>Translation</I>]</FloorLanguage>
              <ParaText id="6099366">We definitely need to co-operate and follow the advice of health officials, who have made it very clear that it is vital to maintain social distancing to prevent the virus from spreading.</ParaText>
              <FloorLanguage language="EN">[<I>English</I>]</FloorLanguage>
              <ParaText id="6099367">In the meantime, we will be where we should be. We will be in our ridings assisting our constituents, pressing to make sure those workers who have to make the difficult choice between putting food on the table or going to work, when they know they should be in self-quarantine, are taken care of. We will be making sure that we are absolutely funding and investing in a health care system that is able to meet the challenges of the virus. We also have to make sure indigenous communities are not left aside, as they have been in past pandemics, and that all the resources they need are available to them.</ParaText>
              <FloorLanguage language="FR">[<I>Translation</I>]</FloorLanguage>
              <ParaText id="6099368">Our role is to be in our ridings assisting the public and ensuring that we contribute to the efforts to fight the virus.</ParaText>
              <FloorLanguage language="EN">[<I>English</I>]</FloorLanguage>
              <ParaText id="6099369">We will do our part. Members of Parliament are speaking with one voice today to say that we will do our part.</ParaText>
              <FloorLanguage language="FR">[<I>Translation</I>]</FloorLanguage>
              <ParaText id="6099370"> Today we are unanimous in saying that we are going to work together. We are going to take a little break to help fight the virus.</ParaText>
              <FloorLanguage language="EN">[<I>English</I>]</FloorLanguage>
              <ParaText id="6099371">To conclude, on behalf of the NDP caucus, I would like to thank the employees and staff, the administration on Parliament Hill, the security guards who are so brave and courageous, and the staff who maintain this infrastructure that serves Canadian democracy so well. We will miss them, but we know we will be back. </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6099372">We know as well that Canadians will beat this virus. We will be able to celebrate that fact when we reconvene.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Timestamp Hr="10" Mn="10">(1010)</Timestamp>
          <FloorLanguage language="FR">[<I>Translation</I>]</FloorLanguage>
          <Intervention Type="Debate" ToC="No" ToCText="Mrs. Mendès" id="10814040">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="253712" Type="93">The Assistant Deputy Speaker (Mrs. Alexandra Mendès)</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="6099373">I thank the member for New Westminster—Burnaby.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6099374">The hon. member for Saanich—Gulf Islands on a point of order.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" id="10814041">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="252941" Type="2">Ms. Elizabeth May</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="6099375">Madam Speaker, I am seeking the unanimous consent of the House to speak.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Debate" ToC="No" ToCText="Mrs. Mendès" id="10814043">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="253712" Type="93">The Assistant Deputy Speaker (Mrs. Alexandra Mendès)</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="6099376">Does the hon. member for Saanich—Gulf Islands have the unanimous consent of the House?</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6099377">
                <B>Some hon. members:</B> Agreed.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <FloorLanguage language="EN">[<I>English</I>]</FloorLanguage>
          <Intervention Type="Question" ToC="Yes" ToCText="Ms. May (Saanich—Gulf Islands)" id="10814044">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="252941" Type="2">Ms. Elizabeth May (Saanich—Gulf Islands, GP)</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="6099378">Madam Speaker, I will not take long, but as this is a unanimous consent motion, I want to put on the record that the Green Party caucus consents. These are not normal times.</ParaText>
              <FloorLanguage language="FR">[<I>Translation</I>]</FloorLanguage>
              <ParaText id="6099379">We are thinking of our friends in the House who are now at risk from the virus. We are thinking of our country. We are thinking of Ms. Grégoire Trudeau and we wish her a speedy recovery. This epidemic affects everyone, all of our loved ones, friends and constituents. </ParaText>
              <Timestamp Hr="10" Mn="15">(1015)</Timestamp>
              <FloorLanguage language="EN">[<I>English</I>]</FloorLanguage>
              <ParaText id="6099380">We cannot tell moment to moment what lies ahead with the spread of COVID-19. I want to express thanks to the Canadian public health authorities at every level and in my own province, particularly B.C. public health officer Bonnie Henry, who has been handling what was quite clearly spreading, and the British Columbia minister of health Adrian Dix and others who have taken strong precautionary action.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6099381">I have confidence in our health authorities. I have confidence in Canadians. We gather in groups, and goodness knows, as members of Parliament, we gather in groups and travel on airplanes. It is incumbent upon us to accept that we have to stop our work in this place. Hopefully it is only for five weeks, so we again can take on the business of the nation. I think it is fair to say that as much as we travel on airplanes, we do not want to find, when history looks at what happened with COVID-19 in Canada, that members of Parliament were vectors of disease. We need to take on board our responsibilities.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6099382">Therefore, I join with all colleagues in thanking our health authorities for their diligence and the <Affiliation DbId="253395" Type="4">Minister of Health</Affiliation>. We are blessed to live in a country with responsible government that does not try to make up the science as it goes along.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6099383"> The Green Party consents to the adjournment and looks forward to seeing everyone again in this place, and in good health.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <FloorLanguage language="FR">[<I>Translation</I>]</FloorLanguage>
          <Intervention Type="Debate" ToC="Yes" ToCText="Mr. Rodriguez" id="10814052">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="253375" Type="4">Hon. Pablo Rodriguez (Leader of the Government in the House of Commons, Lib.)</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="6099384">Madam Speaker, I rise in the House today in extraordinary circumstances.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6099385">I would like to sincerely and warmly thank all the parties in the House for working with us at such an important time.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6099386">I can assure Canadians that the priority of the government and all members of the House is to ensure the health and safety of every Canadian. That is why we are moving the following motion:</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6099387">
                <Quote>
                  <QuotePara Align="Left" IndentFirst="2" IndentRest="1">That, notwithstanding any standing order, special order or usual practice of the House, following the adoption of this order, the House shall stand adjourned until Monday, April 20, 2020, provided that:</QuotePara>
                </Quote>
              </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6099388">
                <Quote>
                  <QuotePara Align="Left" IndentFirst="2" IndentRest="2">(a) the House shall be deemed to have adjourned pursuant to Standing Order 28;</QuotePara>
                </Quote>
              </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6099389">
                <Quote>
                  <QuotePara Align="Left" IndentFirst="2" IndentRest="2">(b) for the supply period ending on March 26, 2020, the eighth allotted day shall be the final allotted day;</QuotePara>
                </Quote>
              </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6099390">
                <Quote>
                  <QuotePara Align="Left" IndentFirst="2" IndentRest="2">(c) the order for the deferred recorded division on the opposition motion standing in the name of the member for Vancouver Kingsway, considered on March 12, 2020, be discharged and the motion be deemed adopted on division;</QuotePara>
                </Quote>
              </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6099391">
                <Quote>
                  <QuotePara Align="Left" IndentFirst="2" IndentRest="2">(d) the motions to concur in Supplementary Estimates (B) for the fiscal year ending on March 31, 2020, and interim supply for the fiscal year ending on March 31, 2021, be deemed adopted on division and the appropriation bills based thereon be deemed to have been introduced and read a first time, deemed read a second time and referred to a committee of the whole on division, deemed considered in committee of the whole, deemed reported without amendment, deemed concurred in at report stage on division, deemed read a third time and passed on division;</QuotePara>
                </Quote>
              </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6099392">
                <Quote>
                  <QuotePara Align="Left" IndentFirst="2" IndentRest="2">(e) there shall be 10 allotted days in the supply period ending on June 23, 2020;</QuotePara>
                </Quote>
              </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6099393">
                <Quote>
                  <QuotePara Align="Left" IndentFirst="2" IndentRest="2">(f) a bill in the name of the Minister of Finance, entitled An Act to amend the Financial Administration Act (special warrant), be deemed to have been introduced and read a first time, deemed read a second time and referred to a committee of the whole on division, deemed considered in committee of the whole, deemed reported without amendment, deemed concurred in at report stage on division, deemed read a third time and passed on division;</QuotePara>
                </Quote>
              </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6099394">
                <Quote>
                  <QuotePara Align="Left" IndentFirst="2" IndentRest="2">(g) currently scheduled committee meetings shall be cancelled;</QuotePara>
                </Quote>
              </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6099395">
                <Quote>
                  <QuotePara Align="Left" IndentFirst="2" IndentRest="2">(h) the order of the day designated for Monday, March 30, 2020, for the consideration of the budget presentation, shall be undesignated;</QuotePara>
                </Quote>
              </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6099396">
                <Quote>
                  <QuotePara Align="Left" IndentFirst="2" IndentRest="2">(i) if, during the period the House stands adjourned, the Speaker receives a notice from the House leaders of all four recognized parties indicating that it is in the public interest that the House remain adjourned until a future date or until future notice is given to the Speaker, the House will remain adjourned accordingly;</QuotePara>
                </Quote>
              </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6099397">
                <Quote>
                  <QuotePara Align="Left" IndentFirst="2" IndentRest="2">(j) Bill C-4, An Act to implement the Agreement between Canada, the United States of America and the United Mexican States, be deemed read a third time and passed;</QuotePara>
                </Quote>
              </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6099398">
                <Quote>
                  <QuotePara Align="Left" IndentFirst="2" IndentRest="2">(k) during the period the House stands adjourned, the House may be recalled, under the provisions of Standing Order 28(3), to consider measures to address the economic impact of COVID-19 and the impacts on the lives of Canadians;</QuotePara>
                </Quote>
              </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6099399">
                <Quote>
                  <QuotePara Align="Left" IndentFirst="2" IndentRest="2">(l) the government’s responses to petitions 431-00042 to 431-00045 be tabled immediately and questions on the Order Paper numbered Q-245 to Q-259 be made into orders for returns and that the said returns be tabled immediately;</QuotePara>
                </Quote>
              </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6099400">
                <Quote>
                  <QuotePara Align="Left" IndentFirst="2" IndentRest="2">(m) the government provide regular updates to representatives of the opposition parties;</QuotePara>
                </Quote>
              </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6099401">
                <Quote>
                  <QuotePara Align="Left" IndentFirst="2" IndentRest="2">(n) any special warrant issued under the Financial Administration Act may be deposited with the Clerk of the House during the period the House is adjourned;</QuotePara>
                </Quote>
              </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6099402">
                <Quote>
                  <QuotePara Align="Left" IndentFirst="2" IndentRest="2">(o) any special warrant issued under the Financial Administration Act and deposited with the Clerk of the House shall be referred to the Standing Committee on Public Accounts and the committee shall meet to consider any warrants referred to it within 20 sitting days; and</QuotePara>
                </Quote>
              </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6099403">
                <Quote>
                  <QuotePara Align="Left" IndentFirst="2" IndentRest="2">(p) the House call on the Auditor General of Canada to immediately conduct an audit of the special warrants issued under the Financial Administration Act and that the Auditor General of Canada report his findings to the House no later than June 1, 2021.</QuotePara>
                </Quote>
              </ParaText>
              <Timestamp Hr="10" Mn="20">(1020)</Timestamp>
              <ParaText id="6099404">Madam Speaker, this decision was taken to help keep all Canadians safe and healthy. We made this decision together, with all the parties, and we did not make it lightly.</ParaText>
              <FloorLanguage language="EN">[<I>English</I>]</FloorLanguage>
              <ParaText id="6099405">Our action today demonstrates that we take this challenge seriously. I want to thank all of the health care workers and professionals.</ParaText>
              <FloorLanguage language="FR">[<I>Translation</I>]</FloorLanguage>
              <ParaText id="6099406">From the bottom of my heart, I want to thank all health care professionals, who are going through tough times at work as they help us through this crisis.</ParaText>
              <FloorLanguage language="EN">[<I>English</I>]</FloorLanguage>
              <ParaText id="6099407">To Canadians, workers and families; to children concerned for their parents; to sisters and brothers concerned for loved ones and friends, we are all united. We will face this together, and we will get through this together.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" id="10814214">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="253712" Type="93">The Assistant Deputy Speaker (Mrs. Alexandra Mendès)</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="6099408">Does the hon. member have the unanimous consent of the House to move the motion?</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6099409">
                <B>Some hon. members:</B> Agreed.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6099410">
                <B>The Assistant Deputy Speaker (Mrs. Alexandra Mendès):</B> The House has heard the terms of the motion. Is it the pleasure of the House to adopt the motion?</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6099411">
                <B>Some hon. members:</B> Agreed. </ParaText>
              <ProceduralText TocType="TCC" id="1">(Motion agreed to)</ProceduralText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
        </SubjectOfBusinessContent>
      </SubjectOfBusiness>
      <SubjectOfBusiness id="10814221">
        <SubjectOfBusinessTitle>
      Opposition Motion—Pharmacare</SubjectOfBusinessTitle>
        <SubjectOfBusinessContent>
          <ProceduralText TocType="TCC" id="2">(Business of Supply. On the Order: Government Orders:)</ProceduralText>
          <ParaText id="6099412">
            <Quote>
              <QuotePara Align="Left" IndentFirst="2" IndentRest="1">March 12, 2020—Mr. Davies (Vancouver Kingsway)—Consideration of motion.</QuotePara>
            </Quote>
          </ParaText>
          <ProceduralText TocType="TCC" id="3">(Motion adopted on division)</ProceduralText>
        </SubjectOfBusinessContent>
      </SubjectOfBusiness>
      <SubjectOfBusiness id="10814282">
        <SubjectOfBusinessTitle>Supplementary Estimates (B)</SubjectOfBusinessTitle>
        <ProceduralText TocType="TCC" id="4">(On the Order: Government Orders:)</ProceduralText>
        <SubjectOfBusinessContent>
          <ParaText id="6099413">
            <Quote>
              <QuotePara Align="Left" IndentFirst="2" IndentRest="1">March 5, 2020—President of the Treasury Board—Consideration of motion to concur in the supplementary estimates (B) for the fiscal year ending March 31, 2020.</QuotePara>
            </Quote>
          </ParaText>
          <ProceduralText TocType="TCC" id="5">(Motion adopted on division)</ProceduralText>
        </SubjectOfBusinessContent>
      </SubjectOfBusiness>
      <SubjectOfBusiness id="10814284">
        <SubjectOfBusinessTitle>Interim Supply</SubjectOfBusinessTitle>
        <SubjectOfBusinessContent>
          <ProceduralText TocType="TCC" id="6">(On the Order: Government Orders:)</ProceduralText>
          <ParaText id="6099414">
            <Quote>
              <QuotePara Align="Left" IndentFirst="2" IndentRest="1">March 5, 2020—President of the Treasury Board—Consideration of motion to concur in interim supply.</QuotePara>
            </Quote>
          </ParaText>
          <ProceduralText TocType="TCC" id="7">(Motion deemed adopted on division)</ProceduralText>
        </SubjectOfBusinessContent>
      </SubjectOfBusiness>
      <SubjectOfBusiness id="10814270">
        <SubjectOfBusinessTitle>Appropriation Act No. 4, 2019-20</SubjectOfBusinessTitle>
        <SubjectOfBusinessContent>
          <ProceduralText TocType="TCC" id="8">(Bill C-10. On the Order: Government Orders:)</ProceduralText>
          <ParaText id="6099415">
            <Quote>
              <QuotePara Align="Left" IndentFirst="2" IndentRest="1">Bill C-10—President of the Treasury Board—Consideration of Bill C-10, An Act for granting to Her Majesty certain sums of money for the federal public administration for the fiscal year ending March 31, 2020.</QuotePara>
            </Quote>
          </ParaText>
          <ProceduralText TocType="TCC" id="9">(Bill introduced, read a first time, read a second time and referred to a committee of the whole on division, considered in committee of the whole and reported without amendment, concurred in at report stage on division, read a third time and passed on division)</ProceduralText>
        </SubjectOfBusinessContent>
      </SubjectOfBusiness>
      <SubjectOfBusiness id="10814320">
        <SubjectOfBusinessTitle>Appropriation Act No. 1, 2020-21</SubjectOfBusinessTitle>
        <SubjectOfBusinessContent>
          <ProceduralText TocType="TCC" id="10">(Bill C-11. On the Order: Government Orders:)</ProceduralText>
          <ParaText id="6099416">
            <Quote>
              <QuotePara Align="Left" IndentFirst="2" IndentRest="1">Bill C-11—President of the Treasury Board—Consideration of Bill C-11, An Act for granting to Her Majesty certain sums of money for the federal public administration for the fiscal year ending March 31, 2021.</QuotePara>
            </Quote>
          </ParaText>
          <ProceduralText TocType="TCC" id="11">(Bill introduced, read the first time, read the second time and referred to committee of the whole on division, considered in committee of the whole and reported without amendment, concurred in at report stage on division, read a third time and passed on division) </ProceduralText>
        </SubjectOfBusinessContent>
      </SubjectOfBusiness>
      <SubjectOfBusiness id="10814343">
        <SubjectOfBusinessTitle>Canada-United States-Mexico Agreement Implementation Act</SubjectOfBusinessTitle>
        <SubjectOfBusinessContent>
          <ProceduralText TocType="TCC" id="12">(Bill C-4. On the Order: Government Orders:)</ProceduralText>
          <ParaText id="6099417">
            <Quote>
              <QuotePara Align="Left" IndentFirst="2" IndentRest="1">March 11, 2020—Deputy Prime Minister and Minister of Intergovernmental Affairs—Third reading stage of Bill C-4, An Act to implement the Agreement
between Canada, the United States of America and the United
Mexican States.</QuotePara>
            </Quote>
          </ParaText>
          <ProceduralText TocType="TCC" id="13">(Bill read the third time and passed)</ProceduralText>
        </SubjectOfBusinessContent>
      </SubjectOfBusiness>
      <SubjectOfBusiness id="10814352">
        <SubjectOfBusinessTitle>Financial Administration Act</SubjectOfBusinessTitle>
        <SubjectOfBusinessContent>
          <ProceduralText TocType="TCC" id="14">(Bill C-12. On the Order: Government Orders:)</ProceduralText>
          <ParaText id="6099418">
            <Quote>
              <QuotePara Align="Left" IndentFirst="2" IndentRest="1">Bill C-12—Minister of Finance—Consideration of Bill C-12, An Act to amend the Financial Administration Act (special warrant).</QuotePara>
            </Quote>
          </ParaText>
          <ProceduralText TocType="TCC" id="15">(Bill introduced, read the first time, read a second time and referred to committee of the whole on division, considered in committee of the whole and reported without amendment, concurred in at report stage on division, read the third time and passed on division)</ProceduralText>
        </SubjectOfBusinessContent>
      </SubjectOfBusiness>
      <SubjectOfBusiness id="10814518">
        <SubjectOfBusinessTitle>Questions Passed as Orders for Returns</SubjectOfBusinessTitle>
        <SubjectOfBusinessContent>
          <FloorLanguage language="Text">[<I>Text</I>]</FloorLanguage>
          <WrittenQuestionResponse>
            <QuestionID>Question No.<Sup> </Sup>245--</QuestionID>
            <Questioner>
              <Affiliation DbId="252994">Mr. Taylor Bachrach</Affiliation>:
						</Questioner>
            <QuestionContent>
              <ParaText id="6099419">With regard to the electoral district of Skeena—Bulkley Valley, between the fiscal year 2005-06 and the current year: what are all the federal infrastructure investments, including direct transfers to municipalities, regional district associations or First Nations, national parks, highways, etc., broken down by fiscal year?</ParaText>
            </QuestionContent>
            <ResponseContent>
              <ParaText id="6099420">(Return tabled)</ParaText>
            </ResponseContent>
          </WrittenQuestionResponse>
          <WrittenQuestionResponse>
            <QuestionID>Question No.<Sup> </Sup>246--</QuestionID>
            <Questioner>
              <Affiliation DbId="252994">Mr. Taylor Bachrach</Affiliation>:
						</Questioner>
            <QuestionContent>
              <ParaText id="6099421">With regard to the Canada Infrastructure Bank: (<I>a</I>) what is the complete list of infrastructure projects financed by the bank since June 1, 2018; (<I>b</I>) for each project in (<I>a</I>), what are the details, including the (i) amount of federal financing, (ii) location of project, (iii) scheduled completion date of project, (iv) project description; and (<I>c</I>) what are the details of projects currently proposed for the bank, including the (i) proposed date of commencement, (ii) location of project, (iii) proposed federal financing, (iv) project description?</ParaText>
            </QuestionContent>
            <ResponseContent>
              <ParaText id="6099422">(Return tabled)</ParaText>
            </ResponseContent>
          </WrittenQuestionResponse>
          <WrittenQuestionResponse>
            <QuestionID>Question No.<Sup> </Sup>247--</QuestionID>
            <Questioner>
              <Affiliation DbId="252994">Mr. Taylor Bachrach</Affiliation>:
						</Questioner>
            <QuestionContent>
              <ParaText id="6099423">With regard to the Investing in Canada Infrastructure Plan: (<I>a</I>) what is the total amount of approved funding; (<I>b</I>) what is the complete list of approved projects; and (<I>c</I>) for each project in (<I>b</I>), what are the details, including the (i) value of approved project, (ii) total amount of federal financing, (iii) location of project, (iv) project description, (v) scheduled completion date?</ParaText>
            </QuestionContent>
            <ResponseContent>
              <ParaText id="6099424">(Return tabled)</ParaText>
            </ResponseContent>
          </WrittenQuestionResponse>
          <WrittenQuestionResponse>
            <QuestionID>Question No.<Sup> </Sup>248--</QuestionID>
            <Questioner>
              <Affiliation DbId="252994">Mr. Taylor Bachrach</Affiliation>:
						</Questioner>
            <QuestionContent>
              <ParaText id="6099425">With regard to the Investing in Canada Infrastructure Plan: (<I>a</I>) what is the total amount of allocated funding not yet spent; (<I>b</I>) what is the complete list of proposed projects not yet assigned federal funding or assigned funding, but not yet commenced construction; and (<I>c</I>) for each project in (<I>b</I>), what are the details, including the (i) value of proposed project, (ii) total amount of federal financing, (iii) location of project, (iv) project description, (v) proposed completion date?</ParaText>
            </QuestionContent>
            <ResponseContent>
              <ParaText id="6099426">(Return tabled)</ParaText>
            </ResponseContent>
          </WrittenQuestionResponse>
          <WrittenQuestionResponse>
            <QuestionID>Question No.<Sup> </Sup>249--</QuestionID>
            <Questioner>
              <Affiliation DbId="252803">Mrs. Shannon Stubbs</Affiliation>:
						</Questioner>
            <QuestionContent>
              <ParaText id="6099427">With regard to the Trans Mountain Pipeline and Expansion Project: (<I>a</I>) what are the revenues generated by the Trans Mountain Pipeline, broken down by quarter, since the pipeline was purchased by the government; (<I>b</I>) what are the operating expenses less loan interest payments to run the Trans Mountain Pipeline, broken down by quarter, since the pipeline was purchased by the federal government; (<I>c</I>) what are the interest payments on the loan used to purchase the Trans Mountain Pipeline, broken down by quarter, since the pipeline was purchased by the government; (<I>d</I>) what is the profit or loss, broken down by quarter, on the Trans Mountain Pipeline since the pipeline was purchased by the government; (<I>e</I>) are the revenues generated by the Trans Mountain Pipeline covering the annual operating and interest payments on the loans the government used to buy the Trans Mountain Pipeline and Expansion; (<I>f</I>) on what date is the pipeline scheduled to be completed, including the month and year; (<I>g</I>) on what date is the pipeline scheduled to enter service, including the month and year; (<I>h</I>) what is the current estimated cost of construction for the Trans Mountain Expansion Project; (<I>i</I>) on what date was the Minister of Finance, or his office, advised in writing or verbally, by officials from either the Department of Finance or a Crown corporation or a government contractor that the estimated cost of construction for the expansion was more than $7.4 billion; and (<I>j</I>) on what date did the government become aware that the cost of completing the Trans Mountain Expansion Project was estimated to be greater than $7.4 billion?</ParaText>
            </QuestionContent>
            <ResponseContent>
              <ParaText id="6099428">(Return tabled)</ParaText>
            </ResponseContent>
          </WrittenQuestionResponse>
          <WrittenQuestionResponse>
            <QuestionID>Question No.<Sup> </Sup>250--</QuestionID>
            <Questioner>
              <Affiliation DbId="252713">Mr. Charlie Angus</Affiliation>:
						</Questioner>
            <QuestionContent>
              <ParaText id="6099429">With regard to the Department of Finance and the Advisory Council on Economic Growth: (<I>a</I>) when and where were each of the council’s meetings held; (<I>b</I>) when were each of the council’s (i) in-person meetings, (ii) phone or video-conference sessions with stakeholders; (<I>c</I>) how much funding was allocated for (i) salaries, (ii) expenses, (iii) council operations, (iv) any other categories of funding not captured by the preceding; (<I>d</I>) how much was spent on (i) salaries, (ii) expenses, (iii) council operations, (iv) any other category of funding not captured by the preceding; and (<I>e</I>) for each of the recommendations in the council’s three reports, (i) what was the recommendation; (ii) which department or departments were tasked with actions following up on the recommendation, (iii) which team or teams within the department or departments were tasked with follow-up actions, (iv) was the action tasked further analysis of or implementation of the recommendation (e.g. feasibility studies or reports), (v) what actions were taken by these teams to implement or further analyze the recommendations?</ParaText>
            </QuestionContent>
            <ResponseContent>
              <ParaText id="6099430">(Return tabled)</ParaText>
            </ResponseContent>
          </WrittenQuestionResponse>
          <WrittenQuestionResponse>
            <QuestionID>Question No.<Sup> </Sup>251--</QuestionID>
            <Questioner>
              <Affiliation DbId="252913">Mr. John Brassard</Affiliation>:
						</Questioner>
            <QuestionContent>
              <ParaText id="6099431">With regard to government aircraft travelling between Canada and Costa Rica between December 15, 2019, and January 10, 2020: what are the details of the legs of each flight to and from Costa Rica, including the (i) type of aircraft, (ii) date, (iii) place of departure, (iv) place of arrival, (v) number of passengers, excluding RCMP protective detail, (vi) name of passengers, excluding RCMP protective detail, (vii) purpose of flight, (viii) food, beverage, and other catering costs?</ParaText>
            </QuestionContent>
            <ResponseContent>
              <ParaText id="6099432">(Return tabled)</ParaText>
            </ResponseContent>
          </WrittenQuestionResponse>
          <WrittenQuestionResponse>
            <QuestionID>Question No.<Sup> </Sup>252--</QuestionID>
            <Questioner>
              <Affiliation DbId="253046">Mr. Eric Melillo</Affiliation>:
						</Questioner>
            <QuestionContent>
              <ParaText id="6099433">With regard to the Federal Economic Development Agency for Northern Ontario (FedNor), since November 4, 2015: (<I>a</I>) what are the details of funding delivered by FedNor in fiscal year (i) 2015-16, (ii) 2016-17, (iii) 2017-18, (iv) 2018-19, (v) 2019-20; (<I>b</I>) for each instances in (<I>a</I>), what are the details, broken down by (i) program or funding stream, (ii) recipient, (iii) address of recipient, including the full address, city and postal code, (iv) mailing address of recipient, including the full address, city and postal code; and (<I>c</I>) for each instances in (<I>b</I>), what was the (i) total funding requested, (ii) total funding granted, (iii) description of project funded, (iv) status of project?</ParaText>
            </QuestionContent>
            <ResponseContent>
              <ParaText id="6099434">(Return tabled)</ParaText>
            </ResponseContent>
          </WrittenQuestionResponse>
          <WrittenQuestionResponse>
            <QuestionID>Question No.<Sup> </Sup>253--</QuestionID>
            <Questioner>
              <Affiliation DbId="252534">Mr. Glen Motz</Affiliation>:
						</Questioner>
            <QuestionContent>
              <ParaText id="6099435">With regard to government statistics related to crimes committed with firearms: (<I>a</I>) how many homicides have been committed in Canada with an AR-15 rifle; (<I>b</I>) how many armed robberies have been committed in Canada where the weapon used was an AR-15 rifle; (<I>c</I>) how many crimes of any sort have been committed in Canada where an AR-15 rifle was present; (<I>d</I>) if the answer to (<I>c</I>) is more than 0, what is the nature of the crime that was committed; (<I>e</I>) how many individuals who have received a Possession and Acquisition License have been convicted of (i) first-degree murder, (ii) second-degree murder, (iii) manslaughter, broken down by year since 2010; (<I>f</I>) how many individuals who have not received a Possession and Acquisition License have been convicted of (i) first-degree murder, (ii) second-degree murder, (iii) manslaughter; (<I>g</I>) for individuals referred to in (<I>e</I>) and (<I>f</I>), how many of these incidents involved a firearm, broken down by year since 2010; (<I>h</I>) how many individuals who have been released on bail and are awaiting trial have been convicted of (i) first-degree murder, (ii) second-degree murder, (iii) manslaughter, broken down by year since 2010; (<I>i</I>) how many individuals who have been released from prison on conditional release have been convicted of (i) first-degree murder, (ii) second-degree murder, (iii) manslaughter, broken down by year since 2010; (<I>j</I>) how many individuals who have been found to have entered Canada illegally have been convicted of (i) first-degree murder, (ii) second-degree murder, (iii) manslaughter, broken down by year since 2010; and (<I>k</I>) how many individuals who have been previously convicted of an organized crime related offence have been convicted of (i) first-degree murder, (ii) second-degree murder, (iii) manslaughter, broken down by year since 2010?</ParaText>
            </QuestionContent>
            <ResponseContent>
              <ParaText id="6099436">(Return tabled)</ParaText>
            </ResponseContent>
          </WrittenQuestionResponse>
          <WrittenQuestionResponse>
            <QuestionID>Question No.<Sup> </Sup>254--</QuestionID>
            <Questioner>
              <Affiliation DbId="252908">Mr. Kyle Seeback</Affiliation>:
						</Questioner>
            <QuestionContent>
              <ParaText id="6099437">With regard to deportation orders issued or in effect by the government since January 1, 2016: (<I>a</I>) what is the total number of orders issued, broken down by year; (<I>b</I>) what was the total number of deportation orders where the deportation was still pending as of (i) January 1, 2016, (ii) January 1, 2017, (iii) January 1, 2018, (iv) January 1, 2019, (v) January 1, 2020; (<I>c</I>) what was the total number of individuals deported, broken down by year; (<I>d</I>) what was the total number of individuals under the age of 18 deported, broken down by year; and (<I>e</I>) how many parents, guardians or adult family members of individuals in (<I>d</I>) were deported, broken down by year?</ParaText>
            </QuestionContent>
            <ResponseContent>
              <ParaText id="6099438">(Return tabled)</ParaText>
            </ResponseContent>
          </WrittenQuestionResponse>
          <WrittenQuestionResponse>
            <QuestionID>Question No.<Sup> </Sup>255--</QuestionID>
            <Questioner>
              <Affiliation DbId="252908">Mr. Kyle Seeback</Affiliation>:
						</Questioner>
            <QuestionContent>
              <ParaText id="6099439">With regard to the Budget 2019 commitment of $1.7 billion for new funding for rural broadband infrastructure: (<I>a</I>) how much of that funding is projected to be spent for broadband projects in the riding of Dufferin—Caledon, broken down by project; (<I>b</I>) what is the breakdown of the $1.7 billion, by project; (<I>c</I>) what are the details of all projects in (<I>b</I>), including the (i) name, (ii) description, (iii) amount of federal contribution, (iv) projected completion date, (v) number of users impacted; and (<I>d</I>) how much of the $1.7 billion has actually been delivered to date, broken down by individual project?</ParaText>
            </QuestionContent>
            <ResponseContent>
              <ParaText id="6099440">(Return tabled)</ParaText>
            </ResponseContent>
          </WrittenQuestionResponse>
          <WrittenQuestionResponse>
            <QuestionID>Question No.<Sup> </Sup>256--</QuestionID>
            <Questioner>
              <Affiliation DbId="252908">Mr. Kyle Seeback</Affiliation>:
						</Questioner>
            <QuestionContent>
              <ParaText id="6099441">With regard to government support programs for agriculture industries impacted by changes in trade with China: (<I>a</I>) in 2019, what is the total amount of government funding provided to the (i) soybean industry, (ii) canola industry, (iii) beef industry; (<I>b</I>) what is the breakdown of all funding in (<I>a</I>), by (i) program, (ii) province; (<I>c</I>) in 2020, what is the projected total amount of government funding to the (i) soybean industry, (ii) canola industry, (iii) beef industry; and (<I>d</I>) what is the breakdown of (<I>c</I>), by (i) program, (ii) province?</ParaText>
            </QuestionContent>
            <ResponseContent>
              <ParaText id="6099442">(Return tabled)</ParaText>
            </ResponseContent>
          </WrittenQuestionResponse>
          <WrittenQuestionResponse>
            <QuestionID>Question No.<Sup> </Sup>257--</QuestionID>
            <Questioner>
              <Affiliation DbId="252954">Mr. Doug Shipley</Affiliation>:
						</Questioner>
            <QuestionContent>
              <ParaText id="6099443">With regard to the government’s policy on firearms: which specific makes and models of weapons that are currently available on the legal market does the government consider to be “military-style assault weapons”?</ParaText>
            </QuestionContent>
            <ResponseContent>
              <ParaText id="6099444">(Return tabled)</ParaText>
            </ResponseContent>
          </WrittenQuestionResponse>
          <WrittenQuestionResponse>
            <QuestionID>Question No.<Sup> </Sup>258--</QuestionID>
            <Questioner>
              <Affiliation DbId="252913">Mr. John Brassard</Affiliation>:
						</Questioner>
            <QuestionContent>
              <ParaText id="6099445">With regard to the awarding of the South West Asia Service Medal (SWASM), the General Campaign Star (GCS), the General Service Medal (GSM) and the South West Asia Service ribbon by the Minister of National Defence for service in Afghanistan: (<I>a</I>) how many have been awarded to date, broken down by award; (<I>b</I>) how many requests for the SWASM have yet to be fulfilled; and (<I>c</I>) what are years of service in which the (i) SWASM, (ii) GSM, (iii) GCS, (iv) South West Asia Service ribbon, are eligible to be awarded, broken down by award?</ParaText>
            </QuestionContent>
            <ResponseContent>
              <ParaText id="6099446">(Return tabled)</ParaText>
            </ResponseContent>
          </WrittenQuestionResponse>
          <WrittenQuestionResponse>
            <QuestionID>Question No.<Sup> </Sup>259--</QuestionID>
            <Questioner>
              <Affiliation DbId="252752">Mr. Blake Richards</Affiliation>:
						</Questioner>
            <QuestionContent>
              <ParaText id="6099447">With regard to the January 15, 2020, Twitter post of the National Capital Commission Rideau Canal Skateway, under the Twitter handle @NCC_Skateway, entitled “Ice Ice Maybe”: (<I>a</I>) what was the total video production cost involved in the planning, production, editing and posting of the video, broken down by (i) work hours of public servants used, (ii) types of expenditure; (<I>b</I>) what are the names and titles of any persons within the government and the National Capital Commission who were involved with the production, planning, editing and posting of the video, including any ministers or ministerial exempt staff that were involved; (<I>c</I>) was any overtime pay granted to public servants as a result of this video, and, if so, what were the details, broken down by (i) the names and titles of managers who signed off, (ii) the total amount and cost of overtime used; (<I>d</I>) what are the details of all documentation on the planning, production, editing and posting of the video, including any scripts, contracts or briefing notes; (<I>e</I>) what are the names and titles of all persons who signed off on and had knowledge of the production of this video; (<I>f</I>) was any paid advertising used to promote the video on Twitter, and, if so, what were the cost and targeting metrics used; (<I>g</I>) were outside services procured in the production of this video, and, if so, what was the name of the company or the persons used and the total cost of any outside contracts, including the (i) date, (ii) amount, (iii) vendor, (iv) summary of goods or services provided; (<I>h</I>) was an outside contract procured, and was there an open request for proposals or was it a sole-sourced contract; and (<I>i</I>) was a music licence sought for the use of the musical likeness of the song “Ice Ice Baby” by the artist Vanilla Ice, and, if so, what were the cost and terms of the licence?</ParaText>
            </QuestionContent>
            <ResponseContent>
              <ParaText id="6099448">(Return tabled)</ParaText>
            </ResponseContent>
          </WrittenQuestionResponse>
          <Intervention Type="Debate" ToC="No" ToCText="Mrs. Mendès" id="10814089">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="253712" Type="93">The Assistant Deputy Speaker (Mrs. Alexandra Mendès)</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="6099449">Pursuant to an order made earlier today, the House stands adjourned until Monday, April 20, 2020 at <?bk ?>11 a.m.<?ek ?> pursuant to Standing Order <?bk ?>28(2)<?ek ?> and <?bk ?>24(1).<?ek ?></ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6099450">(The House adjourned at 10:25 a.m.)</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
        </SubjectOfBusinessContent>
      </SubjectOfBusiness>
    </Intro>
  </HansardBody>
</Hansard>