<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Hansard xml:lang="EN" id="10877253">
  <StartPageNumber>2485</StartPageNumber>
  <DocumentTitle>
    <DocumentName>OFFICIAL REPORT (HANSARD)</DocumentName>
  </DocumentTitle>
  <ExtractedInformation>
    <ExtractedItem Name="InstitutionDebate">House of Commons Debates</ExtractedItem>
    <ExtractedItem Name="Volume">Volume 149</ExtractedItem>
    <ExtractedItem Name="Number">No. 039</ExtractedItem>
    <ExtractedItem Name="Session">1st SESSION</ExtractedItem>
    <ExtractedItem Name="Parliament">43rd PARLIAMENT</ExtractedItem>
    <ExtractedItem Name="Date">Wednesday, June 10, 2020</ExtractedItem>
    <ExtractedItem Name="SpeakerName">Speaker: The Honourable Anthony Rota</ExtractedItem>
    <ExtractedItem Name="Institution">HOUSE OF COMMONS</ExtractedItem>
    <ExtractedItem Name="Country">CANADA</ExtractedItem>
    <ExtractedItem Name="TOCNote">(Table of Contents appears at back of this issue.)</ExtractedItem>
    <ExtractedItem Name="HeaderTitle">COMMONS DEBATES</ExtractedItem>
    <ExtractedItem Name="HeaderDate">June 10, 2020</ExtractedItem>
    <ExtractedItem Name="MetaDocumentCategory">DEBATES</ExtractedItem>
    <ExtractedItem Name="MetaTitle">No. 039</ExtractedItem>
    <ExtractedItem Name="MetaTitleEn">No. 039</ExtractedItem>
    <ExtractedItem Name="MetaTitleFr">N<Sup>o</Sup> 039</ExtractedItem>
    <ExtractedItem Name="MetaVolumeNumber">Volume 149</ExtractedItem>
    <ExtractedItem Name="MetaNumberNumber">039</ExtractedItem>
    <ExtractedItem Name="MetaDateNumDay">10</ExtractedItem>
    <ExtractedItem Name="MetaDateNumMonth">06</ExtractedItem>
    <ExtractedItem Name="MetaDateNumYear">2020</ExtractedItem>
    <ExtractedItem Name="MetaCreationTime">2020/06/10 14:35:00</ExtractedItem>
    <ExtractedItem Name="InstitutionDebateFr">Débats de la Chambre des communes</ExtractedItem>
    <ExtractedItem Name="InstitutionDebateEn">House of Commons Debates</ExtractedItem>
    <ExtractedItem Name="MetaInstitution">House Of Commons</ExtractedItem>
    <ExtractedItem Name="SessionNumber">1</ExtractedItem>
    <ExtractedItem Name="ParliamentNumber">43</ExtractedItem>
    <ExtractedItem Name="InCameraNote">
    </ExtractedItem>
  </ExtractedInformation>
  <HansardBody>
    <Intro>
      <ParaText id="6194401">The House met at 2:30 p.m.</ParaText>
      <Prayer>Prayer</Prayer>
      <SubjectOfBusiness id="10877255">
        <Timestamp Hr="14" Mn="35">(1435)</Timestamp>
        <FloorLanguage language="FR">[<I>Translation</I>]</FloorLanguage>
        <SubjectOfBusinessTitle>Recall of the House of Commons</SubjectOfBusinessTitle>
        <SubjectOfBusinessContent>
          <Intervention Type="Debate" ToC="Yes" ToCText="The Speaker" id="10877256">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="253655" Type="15">The Speaker</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="6194402">Dear colleagues, before we begin our proceedings, I would like to remind you about the special measures in place today.</ParaText>
              <FloorLanguage language="EN">[<I>English</I>]</FloorLanguage>
              <ParaText id="6194403">To that end, pursuant to order made on Tuesday, May 26, the application of Standing Order 17 will be suspended for the current sittings to allow members to practise physical distancing. </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6194404">Members desiring to speak and address the Chair may do so from any seat in the House.</ParaText>
              <FloorLanguage language="FR">[<I>Translation</I>]</FloorLanguage>
              <ParaText id="6194405">I will ask that all members tabling a document or moving a motion sign the document and bring it to the table themselves.</ParaText>
              <FloorLanguage language="EN">[<I>English</I>]</FloorLanguage>
              <ParaText id="6194406">I wish to inform the House that pursuant to order made on Tuesday, May 26, I sent a notice calling the House to meet this day. On Monday, June 8, I sent each member a message explaining the reasons for this recall. I now lay on the table the notice calling the House to meet.</ParaText>
              <FloorLanguage language="FR">[<I>Translation</I>]</FloorLanguage>
              <ParaText id="6194407">Pursuant to an order made on May 26, the House will now proceed to the introduction of government bills.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
        </SubjectOfBusinessContent>
      </SubjectOfBusiness>
    </Intro>
    <OrderOfBusiness id="10877333" Rubric="Other">
      <OrderOfBusinessTitle>Routine Proceedings</OrderOfBusinessTitle>
      <CatchLine>Routine Proceedings</CatchLine>
      <SubjectOfBusiness id="10877332">
        <FloorLanguage language="EN">[<I>English</I>]</FloorLanguage>
        <SubjectOfBusinessTitle>An Act Respecting Additional COVID-19 Measures</SubjectOfBusinessTitle>
        <SubjectOfBusinessContent>
          <Intervention Type="Debate" ToC="Yes" ToCText="Ms. Qualtrough" id="10877352">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="253403" Type="4">Hon. Carla Qualtrough (Minister of Employment, Workforce Development and Disability Inclusion, Lib.) </Affiliation>
            </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ProceduralText TocType="TPC" id="1">Bill C-17. Introduction and first reading</ProceduralText>
              <ParaText id="6194408"> moved for leave to introduce Bill <Document DbId="10788610" Type="3">C-17, An Act respecting additional COVID-19 measures</Document>.</ParaText>
              <ProceduralText TocType="TCC" id="2"> (Motions deemed adopted, bill read the first time and printed) </ProceduralText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" id="10877342">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="253375" Type="4">Hon. Pablo Rodriguez</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="6194409">Mr. Speaker, there have been discussions among the parties and I hope there is agreement to proceed in the following manner. I move: That, pursuant to the order adopted on April 20, 2020, Bill C-17, an act respecting additional COVID-19 measures, be disposed of as follows: a. the bill be ordered for consideration at second reading later this day; b. when the House begins debate on the motion for second reading of the bill, two members of each recognized party and a member of the Green Party may speak to the said motion for not more than 20 minutes, followed by 10 minutes for questions and comments, provided that members may be permitted to split their time with another member; and, at the conclusion of the time provided for the debate or when no member rises to speak, whichever is earlier, all questions necessary to dispose of the second reading stage of the bill shall be put without further debate or amendment, provided that, if a recorded division is requested, it shall not be deferred; and c. if the bill is adopted at second reading, it shall be referred to a committee of the whole, deemed considered in committee of the whole, deemed reported without amendment, deemed concurred in at report stage [on division], and deemed read a third time and passed [on division]. </ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Debate" ToC="No" ToCText="The Speaker" id="10877265">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="253655" Type="15">The Speaker</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="6194410">Does the hon. <Affiliation DbId="253375" Type="4">government House leader</Affiliation> have the unanimous consent of the House to move the motion?</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6194411">
                <B>Some hon. members:</B> Agreed.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6194412">
                <B>Some hon. members:</B> No.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" id="10877270">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="253375" Type="4">Hon. Pablo Rodriguez</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="6194413">Mr. Speaker, there have been discussions among the parties and if you seek it, I hope you will find unanimous consent to adopt the following motion: That Bill <Document DbId="10788610" Type="3">C-17</Document>, an act respecting additional COVID-19 measures, be divided into two bills; that Bill C-17 be entitled “An Act respecting the disclosure of information for the purpose of a one-time permit to persons with disabilities” and consists of part 3 of the said bill and that Bill C-18 be entitled “An Act respecting additional COVID-19 measures” and consists of all the remaining portions of the said bill; and that Bill C-17 be disposed of as follows: </ParaText>
              <Timestamp Hr="14" Mn="40">(1440)</Timestamp>
              <FloorLanguage language="FR">[<I>Translation</I>]</FloorLanguage>
              <ParaText id="6194414"> (a) the bill be ordered for consideration at second reading later this day; (b) when the House begins debate on the motion for second reading of the bill, one member of each recognized party and a member of the Green Party may speak to the said motion for not more than 20 minutes, followed by 10 minutes for questions and comments, provided that members may be permitted to split their time with another member; and, at the conclusion of the time provided for the debate or when no member rises to speak, whichever is earlier, all questions necessary to dispose of the second reading stage of the bill shall be put without further debate or amendment, provided that, if a recorded division is requested, it shall not be deferred; and (c) if the bill is adopted at second reading, it shall be referred to a committee of the whole, deemed considered in committee of the whole, deemed reported without amendment, deemed concurred in at report stage on division, and deemed read a third time and passed on division; Bill C-18 shall be ordered for consideration at second reading at the next sitting of the House; and for the purposes of printing Bills C-17 and C-18, the Law Clerk and Parliamentary Counsel shall be authorized to make any technical changes or corrections in those bills as may be necessary to give effect to this motion. </ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Debate" ToC="No" ToCText="The Speaker" id="10877272">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="253655" Type="15">The Speaker</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="6194415">Does the hon. minister have the unanimous consent of the House to move the motion?</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6194416">
                <B>Some hon. members:</B> Agreed.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6194417">
                <B>Some hon. members:</B> No.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <FloorLanguage language="EN">[<I>English</I>]</FloorLanguage>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" id="10877273">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="232947" Type="96">Hon. Andrew Scheer</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="6194418">Mr. Speaker, I have two unanimous consent motions for which I hope you will find support. The Conservatives, of course, believe that Parliament should be sitting and had we been sitting normally, we could have debated this bill. We could have facilitated the <Affiliation DbId="253375" Type="4">government House leader</Affiliation>'s request, but the government has refused to allow the House to do its work as it normally would.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6194419">Indeed, the proposal that the government has as it relates to people with disabilities was announced several days ago and the House could have been entertaining this legislation as early as Monday.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6194420">I ask for the unanimous consent of the House for the following motion in order to allow the House to debate the legislation that the minister introduced today: that notwithstanding any standing order, or special order or usual practice of the House, when the House adjourns, it shall next meet at 3 p.m. later this day.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Debate" ToC="No" ToCText="The Speaker" id="10877274">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="253655" Type="15">The Speaker</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="6194421">Does the hon. member have the unanimous consent of the House to move the motion?</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6194422">
                <B>Some hon. members:</B> Agreed.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6194423">
                <B>Some hon. members:</B> No.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" id="10877275">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="253375" Type="4">Hon. Pablo Rodriguez</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="6194424">Mr. Speaker, I rise on a point of order. We are here today with a clear opportunity to help people with disabilities. The chance was offered to everybody and the Conservatives said no. That should be noted.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" id="10877277">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="232947" Type="96">Hon. Andrew Scheer</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="6194425">Mr. Speaker, I rise on a point of order. I invite the hon. <Affiliation DbId="253375" Type="4">House leader</Affiliation> to go back, rewind the tape and listen, because members on this side said yes to the House of Commons meeting later today and it was members of the Liberal Party who said no.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Debate" ToC="No" ToCText="The Speaker" id="10877278">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="253655" Type="15">The Speaker</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="6194426">We are getting to a point where we are debating back and forth. I want to remind hon. members that a point of order is usually something on the Standing Orders that we see as not being followed in the House and I want to hear why it is not being followed.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <FloorLanguage language="FR">[<I>Translation</I>]</FloorLanguage>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" id="10877281">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="252770" Type="2">Mr. Alain Therrien</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="6194427">Mr. Speaker, I seek the unanimous consent of the House for the following motion: That the sitting be suspended until such time as the Chair may reconvene the sitting following consultation with the House leaders. </ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Timestamp Hr="14" Mn="45">(1445)</Timestamp>
          <Intervention Type="Debate" ToC="No" ToCText="The Speaker" id="10877283">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="253655" Type="15">The Speaker</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="6194428">Is the member for La Prairie seeking the unanimous consent of the House?</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" id="10877284">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="252770" Type="2">Mr. Alain Therrien</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="6194429">Yes, Mr. Speaker.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Debate" ToC="No" ToCText="The Speaker" id="10877287">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="253655" Type="15">The Speaker</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="6194430">Does the hon. member have the unanimous consent of the House to move the motion?</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6194431">
                <B>Some hon. members:</B> Agreed.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6194432">
                <B>Some hon. members:</B> No.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6194433">
                <B>The Speaker:</B> There is no agreement between the representatives of all the recognized parties to govern today's proceedings. </ParaText>
              <FloorLanguage language="EN">[<I>English</I>]</FloorLanguage>
              <ParaText id="6194434">Accordingly, pursuant to order made on Tuesday, <?bk ?>May 26<?ek ?>, the House stands adjourned until Wednesday, <?bk ?>June 17<?ek ?>, at the conclusion of the proceedings of the Special Committee on the COVID-19 Pandemic.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="6194435">(The House adjourned at 2:46 p.m.)</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
        </SubjectOfBusinessContent>
      </SubjectOfBusiness>
    </OrderOfBusiness>
  </HansardBody>
</Hansard>